<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Docbook XML V.4.3//EN"
	  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
	  <!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
	  %globalent;
	  <!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
	  %gnome-menus-C;
	  <!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
	  %xinclude;
	  <!ENTITY language "en">
	  <!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
	  ]>

<chapter id="applications" status="review">	
	<title>Applications in Ubuntu</title>
	<para>Ubuntu includes a selection of useful applications which are installed by default. You can start an application by pressing <guibutton>Applications</guibutton> and then selecting an application from one of the categories displayed.</para>
	<sect1 id="applications-installing" status="review">
		<title>Installing applications</title>
		<para>Installing applications in Ubuntu is different to Windows. You're probably used to the Add/Remove Applications function in Control Panel. Ubuntu has a similar function that can install as well as remove applications.</para>
		<para>A huge selection of free applications are available stored in repositories. If you would like to install additional applications, press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Add/Remove...</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Then, browse the selection of packages available and check the ones which you would like to install. When you have finished selecting packages, press <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> and wait for the installation process to finish.</para>
		<para>If you know the name of a specific application, you can use <application>Synaptic</application> (&synaptic;).</para>
		<para>The advantage to using these methods are that you will be automatically notified of updates.</para>
		<tip>
			<title>Additional, unsupported software</title>
			<para>You can select <guilabel>Third Party Applications</guilabel> from the <guilabel>Show</guilabel> list box in the <application>Add/Remove...</application> application to see available third party applications.</para>
		</tip>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="applications-equivalents" status="review">
		<title>Ubuntu equivalents to Windows programs</title>
		<para>You can do anything with Ubuntu you could do in Windows. The applications are different however. You can download many of these applications and try them in Windows. What follows is a guide to Ubuntu equivalents.</para>
		<table frame='all'><title>Ubuntu Equivalents to Windows Applications</title>
			<tgroup cols='4' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
				<colspec colname='Windows'/>
				<colspec colname='Ubuntu'/>
				<colspec colname='Where'/>
				<colspec colname='Description'/>
				<thead>
					<row>
  						<entry>Windows</entry>
  						<entry>Ubuntu</entry>
  						<entry>Location</entry>
  						<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
  						<entry>Microsoft Office</entry>
  						<entry><application>Open Office</application></entry>
  						<entry>&open-office;</entry>
  						<entry>It can open Microsoft Office files and supports the Open Document format. Try it now by downloading from <ulink url="http://www.openoffice.org/">OpenOffice.org</ulink></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
  						<entry>Internet Explorer</entry>
  						<entry><application>Mozilla Firefox</application></entry>
  						<entry>&firefox;</entry>
  						<entry>Supports tabbed browsing and can be extended with new skins and extensions. Try it now by downloading from <ulink url="http://www.mozilla.com/en-US/firefox/">Mozilla</ulink>.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Windows Messenger</entry>
  						<entry><application>Pidgin</application></entry>
  						<entry>&pidgin;</entry>
  						<entry>Supports multiple protocols including MSN Messenger, AIM and Yahoo. Try it now by downloading from <ulink url="http://pidgin.im/pidgin/home/">Pidgin</ulink>.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Skype</entry>
  						<entry><application>Ekiga</application></entry>
  						<entry>&ekiga;</entry>
  						<entry>Lets you make audio and video calls over the Internet. It is compatible with Windows Messenger and most VoIP applications. It cannot communicate with Skype, which uses proprietary technology.</entry>
					</row>					
					<row>
						<entry>Outlook</entry>
  						<entry><application>Evolution</application></entry>
  						<entry>&evolution-mail;</entry>
  						<entry>Offers contact and calendar management in addition to being a full featured email client.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Picasa</entry>
  						<entry><application>F-Spot</application></entry>
  						<entry>&f-spot;</entry>
  						<entry>Can import and catalog photos from a wide range of sources, including many digital cameras.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Photoshop</entry>
  						<entry><application>Gimp</application></entry>
  						<entry>&gimp;</entry>
  						<entry>Includes many of Photoshop's features. Try it now by downloading from <ulink url="http://www.gimp.org/">Gimp</ulink>.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Windows Media Player</entry>
  						<entry><application>Totem</application></entry>
  						<entry>&totem;</entry>
  						<entry>Boasts features such as automatic playlists, instant music search and drag-and-drop queueing, but it can even handle podcasts, share music over a network and integrate with the online <emphasis>Last.fm</emphasis> service. What more could you ask for?</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
