<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Docbook XML V.4.3//EN"
	  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
	  <!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
	  %globalent;
	  <!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
	  %cdo-C;
	  <!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
	  %gnome-menus-C;
	  <!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
	  %xinclude;
	  <!ENTITY language "en">
	  <!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
	  ]>

<chapter id="why" status="complete">	
	<title>Why switch to Ubuntu?</title>
	<para>Ubuntu has many advantages over Windows. This chapter discusses the benefits of using Ubuntu and why you might like to switch to using it on your computer.</para>
	<sect1 id="why-stable" status="complete">
		<title>Stable</title>
		<para>Ubuntu is built upon the legendary stability of the Debian GNU/Linux operating system. Wave goodbye to crashes and freezes and say hello to a reliable system which just works.</para>
		<para>The reason for the stability of Ubuntu is the way in which it is created and maintained - if someone finds a stability problem in an Ubuntu application, the problem can be reported and fixed ready for the next release, which will be available within six months. No waiting for service packs, just a working, rock-solid system at your disposal.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Ubuntu applications have been tested by thousands of people world-wide to verify their stability.</emphasis></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Debian GNU/Linux is so stable that it powers some of the most critical computer systems in the world.</emphasis></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Software problems in Ubuntu can be reported and tracked by you, and are often fixed quickly.</emphasis></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="why-secure" status="complete">
		<title>Secure</title>
		<para>The security of your computer is held in the highest regard by the Ubuntu team. Ubuntu offers strong security as standard. Viruses, spyware and adware are practically unheard of in Ubuntu, and security issues are fixed very quickly.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Ubuntu protects important parts of the system from security breaches by limiting how they can be accessed without an administrator password.</emphasis></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Security issues are normally fixed quickly and efficiently, often only a few days after they are reported.</emphasis></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Linux distributions such as Ubuntu are widely used as web servers because of their heavy-duty security.</emphasis></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Ubuntu has an easy to use security update system, which will alert you when new security fixes are available.</emphasis></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="why-easy" status="complete">
		<title>Easy to use</title>
		<para>Ubuntu is <emphasis>Linux for Human Beings</emphasis> - the programs you use are designed around you, the person using them, and are not made any more complex than is absolutely necessary. This does not mean that Ubuntu lacks power, though - the Ubuntu desktop is full of innovative features which other operating systems are only just starting to think about using.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Messages are worded in an unconfusing way, so you only need to read them once.</emphasis></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Your programs are arranged in a way which makes them easy to find.</emphasis></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Programs tend to be uncluttered and streamlined, focusing on the tasks you want to achieve.</emphasis></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="why-international" status="complete">
		<title>International</title>
		<para>Ubuntu can be used by everyone, wherever they live and whatever language they speak. With support for over 100 languages, ranging from Afrikaans to Zulu, and easy access to new translations when they are made, Ubuntu is a truly international operating system. You can even submit your own translations!</para>
		<para>As well as translations, Ubuntu also provides a range of character sets and input methods, so that you can use your computer just as well in any language.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Translations are contributed by a large number of volunteers from around the world.</emphasis></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>You can suggest translations yourself, using the online <application>Rosetta</application> service.</emphasis></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>New language packs can be installed quickly and conveniently, using the <application>Language Support</application> tool.</emphasis></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="why-accessible" status="complete">
		<title>Accessible</title>
		<para>Ubuntu includes a set of accessibility tools by default, including a magnifier, screen reader and on-screen keyboard. Also available are cutting-edge tools such as the innovative <application>Dasher</application> input application and the <application>Orca</application> screenreader.</para>
		<para>The Ubuntu project has an Accessibility Team who are dedicated to making Ubuntu more accessible for everyone.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Accessibility tools are almost always available to you, from the installer to the desktop.</emphasis></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Ubuntu is made more and more accessible each release.</emphasis></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>You can help make Ubuntu more accessible by contacting the Accessibility Team and reporting any problems you experience.</emphasis></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="why-free" status="complete">
		<title>Free</title>
		<para>Ubuntu is free and open-source. We will never charge you to install and use Ubuntu, and you can always access, modify, use and distribute our supported applications. In fact, you are encouraged to do so! Not only does this mean that you save money on your software, it also means that the software you use is completely transparent and open to scrutiny. Security problems are found faster, no nasty surprises can be included without your knowledge and you can even make changes to Ubuntu yourself. Freedom!</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>If you have the technical knowledge to do so, you can modify your favorite applications yourself.</emphasis></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Anyone can use Ubuntu, no matter who they are.</emphasis></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="why-community" status="complete">
		<title>Community</title>
		<para>The community underlies everything that Ubuntu does; without the community, Ubuntu would not be the world-class operating system that it is today. From providing translations, testing and support to writing new software and fixing problems, the community is integral to the success of Ubuntu. Anyone can get involved, as much or as little as they like. You can help to shape the direction of the Ubuntu project and improve software for people all over the world.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>Anyone can contribute to Ubuntu, no matter who they are.</emphasis></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>The Ubuntu Code of Conduct and Community Council help to guide the community and ensure everyone has a fair chance of having their say.</emphasis></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><emphasis>There are numerous teams and projects within Ubuntu for people with different interests and ideas.</emphasis></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
