<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % genericent SYSTEM "../../libs/generic.ent">
%genericent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>

<chapter id="faq" status="needshelp">
	<title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
	<para>Security-related questions are asked on support forums on a daily basis.  Answers
	to these questions are varied.  There is more than one right answer to most of them, and
	most of them require and deserve more thorough coverage than they generally get on these
	forums.  We will address some of the most frequently asked general security questions here.
	</para>
	
	<itemizedlist>

		<listitem>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">Do I need a firewall?</emphasis></para>
			<para>It can't hurt.  A properly configured firewall can protect your machine and your
			network from the hostile world of the Internet, where worms, viruses, and nefarious
			individuals are on constant missions to take control of your systems.  Don't let this
			lull you into a false sense of security, though; running a firewall does not excuse
			you from security best-practices, such as keeping your software up to date, shutting
			down unnecessary services, etc.  While your firewall can in fact provide significant
			protection on its own, its job is to be the first line of defense in a multi-layered
			security strategy.</para>
		</listitem>
		
		<listitem>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">Do I need anti-virus software?</emphasis></para>
			<para>Security is about trade-offs.  Nearly everything you do to secure your system
			will involve some kind of sacrifice.  You may be sacrificing performance, usability,
			maintainability, your precious time, stability, or in a few pleasant cases, nothing
			at all.  Whether a security measure is a good idea is determined by asking yourself
			whether the cost is worth the mitigated risk.  A firewall is almost always a good
			idea, because it provides a significant amount of protection from a wide range of
			threats without, if properly configured, interfering too much in your activities or
			requiring a great deal of maintenance.  Once it's up and running, you can almost
			forget it's there.</para>
			<para>There are rumors that Linux is impervious to viruses.  While it is true that
			Linux systems are much more resistant to viruses than Windows systems, and much
			more difficult to infect, this is not the case.  No virus (if we distinguish viruses
			from worms) has ever been found infecting Linux machines in the wild, but it's not
			inconceivable that one could appear in the future.  If it does, it is not likely to
			be very successful.  Most Linux users - responsible Linux users - do not perform
			their daily activities, such as surfing the Internet, checking email, etc., with
			administrative (root) privileges.  For this and other reasons, a virus would have
			a difficult time infecting system files or spreading itself further.</para>
			<para>To summarize the virus risk, it is unlikely but possible that you will ever
			encounter a virus threat to your Linux system.  Anti-virus products are popular on
			Windows systems because the threat to them is much greater.  If security is of
			paramount importance to you, you should consider installing an anti-virus system,
			but you should be aware of the cost.  For anti-virus software to protect effectively,
			it must scan executable files whenever they are downloaded or executed.  This can
			have an enormous impact on the performance of your system.  There is an administrative
			cost, too.  Virus definitions must be updated regularly -- preferably daily.  While
			this can usually be set up once and forgotten, the antivirus engines must also be
			updated.  As with most Linux distributions, &ubuntu; usually backports security
			updates and bugfixes to software in its repositories for stable releases.  This means
			that your anti-virus engine will need to be updated from outside the official
			repositories to maintain its ability to cope with new virus threats.  Finally,
			since anti-virus software is just as prone to bugs as any other software, and since
			it must scan all your executable files, libraries, documents, etc., it poses a risk
			to the stability of your system as well.  In short, an anti-virus system may be worth
			the cost to some users, but most choose to omit it from their security arsenals.  The
			decision is yours to make.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">I don't have any sensitive information on my machine.
			Why should I care about security?</emphasis></para>
			<para>An unfortunately common attitude on the Internet is that security is only
			important to those with sensitive information stored on their computers.  It is
			critical to debunk this myth.  First, you probably have sensitive information on your
			machine whether you're aware of it or not.  You might instruct your browser to save
			passwords to secure websites, like your banking site.  Your email client may store
			authentication information for your mail server, where sensitive information may
			also be stored, and where it is available to anyone who gains access to your username
			and password.</para>
			<para>Even if you truly have no personal motivation to protect the information on
			your system, though, it is irresponsible and destructive for you to ignore security
			concerns.  Most of the security threats on the Internet do not have the goal of
			uncovering secrets stored on your computer.  They seek to gain access to your system
			in order to use it as a platform for launching attacks on other machines.  If one of
			the unscrupulous citizens of the Internet takes advantage of an unsecured machine, he
			may or may not look for sensitive information.  He is much more likely to turn your
			machine into a <quote>zombie</quote>, without your knowledge, and have it wait to do
			his bidding.  At the attacker's command, your machine will be used to participate in
			distributed attacks on other networks, to send spam as fast as your computer can send
			it, or to launch a targeted attack on another network, masking the attacker's identity
			by making the attack appear to originate from your system.</para>
			<para>Security is important, then, not only to protect yourself, but to help make the
			Internet a safer place by ensuring that your computer and its resources are not
			subverted for the purpose of attacking others.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">How secure is Linux?</emphasis></para>
			<para>Security is a guiding principle behind the development of Linux and most Linux
			software.  It also benefits, like all open source software, from the fact that its
			code can be audited for security problems by anyone with the expertise to do so.
			&ubuntu; as a distribution is also very security-conscious and adheres to a list of
			rules that help to keep it as secure as possible out of the box while maintaining
			usability.  Additionally, &ubuntu; benefits from the efforts of Debian's famed
			security team.  But in the end, a Linux machine -- like any other machine -- is only
			as secure as its administrator makes it.  A freshly installed &ubuntu; machine has
			no ports open to the outside world, which helps to make it very secure against
			external threats, but users inevitably install software that (out of necessity)
			exposes itself to the Internet, making it less secure.  If these applications are
			properly configured and kept up to date, they should not represent a significant
			threat to security, but it is your responsibility as the administrator to do these
			things.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para id="secure-passwords" xreflabel="secure password">
			<emphasis role="bold">How long is a secure password?</emphasis></para>
			<para>Obviously there is no cutoff point where one could call a password of a certain
			length <quote>secure</quote> and all shorter passwords <quote>insecure</quote>.  Also,
			there are other factors than length that contribute to the effectiveness of a password.
			The more <emphasis role="italics">character classes</emphasis> in your password, the
			more secure it is.  Character classes include uppercase letters, lowercase letters,
			numbers, and special characters or punctuation.  Any password that can be found in a
			dictionary is vulnerable to a <emphasis role="italics">dictionary attack</emphasis>
			and is therefore insecure.  Appending digits to the end of a dictionary password does
			not significantly enhance its security.  A password like <quote>forest179</quote>
			would succumb to a dictionary attack in a few seconds.  A password like
			<quote>9gIn$nf2Y_!</quote> is reasonably secure against all forms of brute force
			attacks, because it is not in any dictionary, it is 11 characters long, and it uses
			all character classes (except non-printable characters, which are unsupported in some
			interfaces).
			</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">Should I write down my password?</emphasis></para>
			<para>The consensus on this question has shifted in recent years from an emphatic
			<quote>No</quote> to a cautious <quote>Yes</quote>.  The problem is that as computers
			get faster, it becomes harder to choose a password that a user can remember, but
			which is still secure.  The concept of password authentication is meant to solve the
			problem of proving who you are to the authenticating system.  A password is,
			theoretically, something that only you know, so providing it to the system is supposed
			to prove who you are.  If someone else can obtain your password, the system breaks.
			If you write down your password, it may be easier for an attacker to obtain that piece
			of paper than to get into your head, so that practice has historically been considered
			insecure.  But as computers become more powerful, it becomes easier to obtain unwritten
			passwords without getting into your head, because you are likely to choose a password
			that can be broken, because the things that make it easy to remember (it's short, it's
			a word or phrase that can be pronounced, etc.) are the same things that make it easy to
			break.  Choosing a more secure password that's difficult to remember, and writing that
			password down, may help to solve that problem (if you keep your password in a safe
			place - don't tape it to your monitor!).  The authentication system is now based on
			<quote>something you have</quote> rather than <quote>something you know</quote>.
			Many, but certainly not all, security experts now agree that choosing a difficult
			password and writing it down is more likely to provide securite than trying to choose a 
			good password that you can remember.</para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
			<para><emphasis role="bold">How can I make my system more secure?</emphasis></para>
			<para>
			There are many steps you can take to secure your system.  Some of these steps are
			more effective than others, but the most important consideration is that your system
			is secure <emphasis role="italics">in depth</emphasis>.  If your first line of
			defense fails or is defeated, another countermeasure should be right behind it to
			back it up.  For example, if you're too confident in your firewall and trust it as
			your only security measure, matters will be much worse if and when it fails than if
			you had secured your system in depth.</para>
			<para>Specific steps you can take to secure your system will be covered in detail in
			this document.  If you're looking for the most useful information with the least
			possible text, the following list should get you started:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Don't run--or even install--unnecessary software; the more software 
				you have running, the more possible points of failure you have.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>For software that you do run, especially servers, ensure that it is not
				available (does not <quote>listen</quote>) on network interfaces or addresses
				that are not necessary.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>All software, especially server software, especially server software
				that listens on an Internet-facing device, should be configured as securely as
				possible while still providing necessary functionality.  Remember the <xref
				linkend="least-privilege" />.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>A good firewall can protect you against many attacks to which you might
				otherwise be vulnerable.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>A <xref linkend="secure-passwords" /> is an absolute requirement for a
				secure system. (Note that secure non-password authentication counts as a secure
				password.)</para></listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>
	
		<listitem>
			<para id="least-privilege" xreflabel="principle of least privilege"><emphasis
			role="bold">What is the Principle of Least Privilege?</emphasis></para>
			<para>The principle of least privilege states that a system operates with the most
			restrictive set of permissions possible that still allows it to perform its required
			functions.  A system can be a user, a piece of software, a computer, a network, or
			even a person.  The more privileges a system has, the more damage it can do to
			other systems if its security is compromised.  So, if each system operates under the
			principle of least privilege, all systems are safer because damage is limited in the
			event one of the systems is compromised.</para>
		</listitem>
	
	</itemizedlist>
</chapter>
