<chapter id="styleguide-confused">
	<title>Commonly Confused Words</title>
	<para>There are many words in the English language which cause problems for writers of all skill levels. Some of the more common ones are listed below.</para>
	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
		<term><emphasis role="bold">accept, except</emphasis></term>
			<listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">Accept</emphasis> means to agree to, or to receive. <emphasis role="italic">Except</emphasis> means to exclude or to leave out.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		<term><emphasis role="bold">advice, advise</emphasis></term>
			<listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">Advice</emphasis> is an opinion about what should be done about a problem or situation. <emphasis role="italic">Advise</emphasis> is a verb, meaning to give advice to.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		<term><emphasis role="bold">affect, effect</emphasis></term>
			<listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">Affect</emphasis> is a verb meaning to influence. An <emphasis role="italic">effect</emphasis> is a result, outcome, or consequence of an action or event.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		<term><emphasis role="bold">a lot, allot</emphasis></term>
			<listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">A lot</emphasis> is a two-word phrase meaning a great deal or a large amount. It is never &quot;alot.&quot; <emphasis role="italic">Allot</emphasis> means to give out or to allow to have.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		<term><emphasis role="bold">assure, ensure, insure</emphasis></term>
			<listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">Assure</emphasis> means to make a promise or commitment. <emphasis role="italic">Ensure</emphasis> is to make certain or to make secure. <emphasis role="italic">Insure</emphasis> means to provide or obtain insurance.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		<term><emphasis role="bold">a while, awhile</emphasis></term>
			<listitem>
        <para>The two-word phrase <emphasis role="italic">a while</emphasis> is a noun, and functions as a subject or an object in a sentence. Awhile is an adverb meaning for a short time. <emphasis role="italic">Awhile</emphasis> is never preceded by a preposition; in that case use the two-word form. For example, you can stay awhile, or you can stay for a while.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		<term><emphasis role="bold">complement, compliment</emphasis></term>
			<listitem>
        <para>As a noun, <emphasis role="italic">complement</emphasis> is something that completes or make makes up a whole, or brings to perfection. As a verb, complement means to complete. <emphasis role="italic">Compliment</emphasis> means to praise, and as a noun, it is an expression of praise.</para>
        <para>Examples: Documentation complements a software application. The supervisor complimented her employees on their work.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		<term><emphasis role="bold">everyday, every day</emphasis></term>
			<listitem>
        <para>The single word <emphasis role="italic">everyday</emphasis> is an adjective, and means &quot;daily&quot; or &quot;normal.&quot; The two-word phrase <emphasis role="italic">every day</emphasis> is an adverbial phrase, and is used only to modify verbs.</para>
        <para>Examples: Writing is an everyday occurrence. I wrote something every day last week.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		<term><emphasis role="bold">fewer, less</emphasis></term>
			<listitem>
        <para>Use <emphasis role="italic">fewer</emphasis> for nouns that can be counted: fewer words, fewer ideas, fewer people. Use <emphasis role="italic">less</emphasis> for collective nouns: less money, less hair, less work.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><emphasis role="bold">good, well</emphasis></term>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">Good</emphasis> is an adjective, and <emphasis role="italic">well</emphasis> is an adverb</para>
        <para>Examples: The employees did a good job. (good modifies the noun job) The employees did their job well. (well modifies the verb did)</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		<term><emphasis role="bold">its, it's</emphasis></term>
			<listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">Its</emphasis> is the possessive form of the pronoun &quot;it.&quot; <emphasis role="italic">It's</emphasis> is a contraction of &quot;it is&quot; or &quot;it has.&quot;</para>
        <para>Examples: The dog ate its food. It's a good day to write.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		<term><emphasis role="bold">principal, principle</emphasis></term>
			<listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">Principal</emphasis> is generally used as an adjective, and means &quot;chief,&quot; &quot;leading,&quot; or &quot;primary.&quot;  <emphasis role="italic">Principle</emphasis> is a noun only. In a technical writing context, principle is typically used to describe a basic or fundamental mode of behavior of a system or machine.</para>
        <para>Examples: The automobile is the principal means of transportation in North America. You must understand a machine's principle of operation before writing the manual.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		<term><emphasis role="bold">rational, rationale</emphasis></term>
			<listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">Rational</emphasis> is an adjective, and is used to indicate  that something is based on reason or is logical. <emphasis role="italic">Rationale</emphasis> is a fundamental reason or basis.</para>
        <para>Examples: The team made a rational decision. The rationale for the team's decision was explained to the manager.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		<term><emphasis role="bold">than, then</emphasis></term>
			<listitem>
        <para>The most common mistake made with these words is to use <emphasis role="italic">then</emphasis> in place of <emphasis role="italic">than</emphasis>. Only use <emphasis role="italic">then</emphasis> when describing something that comes next in order. Use <emphasis role="italic">than</emphasis> in comparisons.</para>
        <para>Examples: Working with XML can be more useful than working with HTML. I wrote the standards then uploaded them to the web site.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		<term><emphasis role="bold">their, there, they're</emphasis></term>
			<listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">Their</emphasis> and <emphasis role="italic">there</emphasis> are frequently used incorrectly, despite having distinctly different meanings. <emphasis role="italic">Their</emphasis> is used to indicate possession or ownership, and <emphasis role="italic">there</emphasis> is used to indicate position or to introduce a clause or sentence. <emphasis role="italic">They're</emphasis> is simply the contraction of &quot;they are.&quot;</para>
        <para>Examples: The writers left their pens at home. There are writers over there. They're discussing their lack of pens.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		<term><emphasis role="bold">to, too, two</emphasis></term>
			<listitem>
        <para>The most common error here is to use <emphasis role="italic">to</emphasis> in place of <emphasis role="italic">too</emphasis>. <emphasis role="italic">Too</emphasis> means &quot;also,&quot; &quot;in addition,&quot; or &quot;more than enough.&quot; Use <emphasis role="italic">to</emphasis> in all other cases. <emphasis role="italic">Two</emphasis> is the number &quot;2.&quot;</para>
        <para>Examples: I went to the store too. There are too many writers in the room. There are two writers in the room.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
		<term><emphasis role="bold">your, you're</emphasis></term>
			<listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">Your</emphasis> is used to indicate possession or ownership, and <emphasis role="italic">you're</emphasis> is the contraction of &quot;you are.&quot;</para>
        <para>Examples: You're driving your car to the store.</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
</chapter>

