<chapter id="styleguide-intro">
	<title>Introduction</title>
	<sect1 id="intro-1">
		<title>Overview of the Style Guide</title>
		<para>A style guide is a reference tool used by writers and editors. It is an outline of the policies and standards that writers and editors are expected to work to.</para>
		<para>The Ubuntu documentation team needs its own style guide because Ubuntu is unique. Ubuntu is Linux + GNU + Debian + (GNOME and KDE) + the Ubuntu philosophy. No style guide covers the entire spectrum of Ubuntu components.</para>
		<para>The Ubuntu Documentation Style Guide is built with the participation of the members of the Ubuntu documentation team, and represents the current accepted practice for documents produced and maintained by the docteam.</para>
		<para>This style guide attempts to achieve the following:</para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>Help writers communicate clearly.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Create a consistent style across all documents.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Create a consistent use of terminology across all documents.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Highlight common problems in the use of the English language, and to provide solutions.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Help writers write for an international audience, including how to write for translation.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Help writers and editors select the appropriate DocBook markup.</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
		<para>This style guide contains three main types of information:</para>
	<orderedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>Material that is unique to Ubuntu documentation.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Material that may be helpful to writers, but is not covered in other guides.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Material that is covered in other guides, but is either summarized or repeated here for convenience.</para>
		</listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="intro-2">
		<title>Style Guide Applicability and Precedence</title>
		<para>The Ubuntu style guide is applicable to all documents produced by or for the Ubuntu documentation team. It covers all documents in the docteam's SVN repository.</para>
		<para>The docteam may decide to take official responsibility for a limited number of important wiki pages; the style guide will be applicable to those pages.</para>
		<para>The Ubuntu style guide takes precedence over all other style guides. Where there is a conflict between this style guide and any other style guide, the Ubuntu Documentation Style Guide shall prevail.</para>
		<para>If you encounter a topic or situation that is not covered by this style guide, then refer to the GNOME Documentation Style Guide. If your document deals exclusively with KDE, then refer to the KDE Style Guide.</para>
		<para>If you have still not found a solution after referring to one of the guides above, then you will have to make your own decision. See the Reference Materials section for links to other style guides and documentation handbooks.</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>

