<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<article id="add-applications" status="review">
	<articleinfo>
	<title>Adding, Removing and Updating Applications</title>
    	&legalnotice;
	</articleinfo>
	<para>This section discusses how applications are installed, removed and kept up to date. Also covered are how packages are stored by Ubuntu and made available for download.</para>
	<para>It also covers some more advanced techniques for managing applications.</para>
	<sect1 id="add-applications-introduction" status="review">
		<title>What is a package manager?</title>
		<para>A package manager is used to install, remove and upgrade software. Linux software often requires other programs to run - a package manager can also find, download and install these. Such programs are known as dependancies.</para>
		<para>There are three main package management programs you can use in Ubuntu:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para><link linkend="gnome-app-install"><application>Add/Remove Applications</application></link> - Quickly installs and removes popular programs, as well as providing ratings.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><link linkend="synaptic"><application>Synaptic</application></link> - Allows more advanced management, such as installing applications by task.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para><link linkend="apt"><application>Apt</application></link> - Allowing package management from the command line.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<note>
			<para>These three methods all access the program to install software called dpkg. This means that if you try to open more than one, the new instance will not open.</para>
		</note>
		<note>
			<para>Most package management tasks require administrative access, see (<ulink type="help" url="ghelp:administrative">Administrative Tasks</ulink> for more details.</para>
		</note>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="extra-repositories" status="review">
		<title>Software repositories</title>
		<para>A software repository is a place from which you can download and install software over the Internet.</para>
		<para>There are thousands of programs available to install on Ubuntu. These programs are stored in software archives (<emphasis>repositories</emphasis>) and are made freely available for installation over the Internet. This makes it very easy to install new programs in Linux, and it is also very secure, because each program you install is built specially for Ubuntu and checked before it is installed.</para>
		<para>To organise the software, Ubuntu repositories are categorised into four groups: <emphasis>Main</emphasis>, <emphasis>Restricted</emphasis>, <emphasis>Universe</emphasis>, and <emphasis>Multiverse</emphasis>. The rationale used to determine which software goes into which category is based on the level of support that software development teams provide for a program and the level of compliance the program has to the <ulink url="&ubuntu-philosophy;">Free Software Philosophy</ulink>.</para>
		<para>The standard Ubuntu Install CD contains some software from the <emphasis>Main</emphasis> and <emphasis>Restricted</emphasis> categories.</para>
		<para>If your system is connected to the Internet, many more software programs are made available for installation. For example, the <quote>Universe</quote> and <quote>Multiverse</quote> repositories are only available over the Internet.</para>
		<warning>
			<para>The <emphasis>Multiverse</emphasis> repository contains software which has been classified as <emphasis>non-free</emphasis>. This software may not be permitted in some jurisdictions. When installing each package from this repository, you should verify that the laws of your country permit you to use it. Also, this software may not include security updates.</para>
		</warning>
		<para>You can find more information about the Repositories available <ulink url="&ubuntu-components;">on the website</ulink>.</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="extra-repositories-adding" status="review">
		<title>Adding extra repositories</title>
		<para>It is possible to add extra repositories, such as those provided by third parties or those for older version of Ubuntu.</para>
		<caution>
			<para>Be careful when installing software from third-party repositories. It may not have been tested with Ubuntu and could cause your system to break.</para>
		</caution>
		<procedure>
			<step>
				<para>Open &software-properties; and press <guilabel>Third Party Software</guilabel>.</para>
			</step>
			<step>
				<para>Press <guibutton>Add</guibutton> to add a new repository.</para>
			</step>
			<step>
				<para>Enter the <guilabel>APT line</guilabel> for the extra repository. This should be available from the website of the repository or similar, and should look similar to the following:</para>
<screen>deb http://ftp.debian.org etch main</screen>
			</step>
			<step><para>Press <guibutton>Add Source</guibutton> and then click <guibutton>Close</guibutton> to save your changes.</para>
			</step>
			<step><para>You will be notified that the information about available software is out-of-date. Press <guibutton>Reload</guibutton>.</para>
			</step>
			<step><para>Most software repositories use a GPG key to digitally sign the files they provide, which makes it easy to check that the files have not been tampered with since their creation.  In order for apt to be able to check this, you need the public key that corresponds to the signatures.  The key should be available for download on the repository's website.</para>
			</step>
			<step><para>Once you have downloaded the GPG key, import the key by selecting the <guilabel>Authentication</guilabel> tab, clicking on <guibutton>Import Key File</guibutton>, and then selecting the GPG key to be imported.</para>
			</step>
		</procedure>
	</sect1>
  <sect1 id="gnome-app-install" status="review">
		<title>Add/Remove Applications</title>
		<para>With the <guimenuitem>Add/Remove</guimenuitem> item in the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu, you can install programs to do new things with Ubuntu. You can also remove programs which you do not want. You need administrative access to use <application>Add/Remove Applications</application> (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:administrative">Administrative Tasks</ulink> for more details).</para>
		<para>If you know the name of a program you want to install, enter it in the <guilabel>Search</guilabel> field. Otherwise, begin by choosing a software category on the left.</para>
		<para>Programs that are already installed have a check mark next to their name. Uncheck a program if you want to remove it from your computer.</para>
		<para>When you click <guibutton>Apply Changes</guibutton>, any new software will be downloaded from the Internet, and Ubuntu will make any other changes you selected. If you have not activated the online package archive, you may be asked to insert your Ubuntu CD-ROM to install some packages.</para>
    <para>Some software cannot be installed or removed using <application>Add/Remove Applications</application>. If you cannot find the package you are looking for, start the advanced package manager <application>Synaptic</application> (see <xref linkend="advanced"/>).
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="offline" status="review">
		<title>Installing packages without an Internet connection</title>
		<para>Other than using tools that download packages automatically, it is also possible to use a CD to install packages through a package manager while not connected to the Internet. The Ubuntu installation CD can be used for this purpose, and other CDs with different packages are available as well. Additionally, the program <application>APTonCD</application> can automatically backup installed packages on your system, and create CDs with the contents of various repositories on them.</para>
		<sect2 id="ubuntu-installation-cd" status="review">
			<title>Installing packages using the Ubuntu installation CD</title>
				<para>Some packages from the <emphasis>main</emphasis> and <emphasis>restricted</emphasis> Ubuntu package repositories can be installed from the Ubuntu installation CD. Simply insert your Ubuntu installation CD and open &synaptic;. To list only packages on the Ubuntu installation CD, click on the <guibutton>Origin</guibutton> button in the lower left corner of <application>Synaptic Package Manager</application>. The packages should be listed under the <guimenuitem>&distro-apt-cd-name;</guimenuitem> section.</para>
				<para>If the packages are not listed, it may be because the CD is not listed as a package repository (the CD should be listed as a repository by default). To add the CD as a package repository, follow the instructions in <xref linkend="repository-cds"/>, below.</para>	
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="repository-cds" status="review">
			<title>Enabling other CDs that can be used to install packages</title>
			<para>To enable <application>Synaptic</application> and other package managers to install software from CDs which contain packages:</para>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para>Press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>System</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Administration</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Software Sources</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para> 
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>Go to the <guilabel>Third Party Software</guilabel> tab and click on the <guibutton>Add CD-ROM</guibutton> button.</para>
				</step> 
				<step>
					<para>Insert the CD.</para>
				</step>
			</procedure>
			<para>The packages should then be listed. To have <application>Synaptic</application> only list packages from the CD, click the <guibutton>Origin</guibutton> button on the lower left corner of <application>Synaptic Package Manager</application>, then find the name of the CD on the list in the upper left corner of <application>Synaptic</application>.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="APTonCD" status="review">
			<title>Using APTonCD to install packages</title>
			<para><application>APTonCD</application> can be used to create a CD that contains all the packages you have on your system, or it can create CDs with packages or entire repositories of your choice. In a package manager such as <application>Synaptic</application>, find the <emphasis>aptoncd</emphasis> package and install it.</para>
			<para>Further documentation on <application>APTonCD</application> can be found on its website, <ulink url="http://aptoncd.sourceforge.net">aptoncd.sourceforge.net</ulink></para>
		</sect2> 
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="advanced" status="review">
		<title>Advanced package management</title>
			<para>Several other package managers exist in Ubuntu. These contain more advanced features than <application>Add/Remove Applications</application>.</para>
	<sect2 id="synaptic" status="review">
		<title>Synaptic Package Manager</title>
		<para><application>Synaptic</application> is an advanced package management application that can install and remove every package available to your system. The interface is graphical like <application>Add/Remove Applications</application>, but presents much more information and gives you complete control over the software on your computer.</para>
		<para>To launch <application>Synaptic</application>, press &synaptic;.
			You need administrative access to use <application>Synaptic</application>; see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:administrative">Administrative Tasks</ulink> for more details.</para>
		<para>If you know the name of the package you want to install or remove, click the <guibutton>Search</guibutton> button, and enter the package name or a short search term. You can also search for packages by description (for example, you can find all packages mentioning <quote><wordasword>arcade</wordasword></quote> or <quote><wordasword>mathematics</wordasword></quote>).</para>
		<para>Use the categories on the left to filter the list of packages. To return to the list of categories after doing a search, click <guibutton>Sections</guibutton>.</para>
		<para>To install a package, click the box next to it and choose <guimenuitem>Mark for installation</guimenuitem>. If you change your mind, choose <guimenuitem>Unmark</guimenuitem>.</para>
		<para>To remove a package that is already installed, choose <guimenuitem>Mark for Removal</guimenuitem>.</para>
		<para>When you have finished, click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> and Ubuntu will make the changes you selected. If you do not want to make any changes, close the window instead.</para>
	</sect2>
    <sect2 id="apt" status="review">
      <title>Command-line package management with APT</title>
      <para>If you are comfortable using the Terminal, you can use
      <application>apt</application> (Advanced Packaging Tool) to
      install or remove software. You need administrative access to
      use <application>apt</application>; see <ulink type="help"
      url="ghelp:administrative">Administrative Tasks</ulink> for more
      details.
      </para>
      <para>
	To update the local list of packages, enter in a Terminal:
	<screen>sudo apt-get update</screen>
      </para>
      <para>
	To install all available updates:
	<screen>sudo apt-get upgrade</screen>
      </para>
      <para>
	To search for a package:
	<screen>apt-cache search <replaceable>package</replaceable></screen>
      </para>
      <para>
	To install a package:
	<screen>sudo apt-get install <replaceable>package</replaceable></screen>
      </para>
      <para>
	To remove a package:
	<screen>sudo apt-get remove <replaceable>package</replaceable></screen>
      </para>
      <para>
	To remove a package and all its dependancies (that are not in use by other programs):
	<screen>sudo apt-get autoremove <replaceable>package</replaceable></screen>
      </para>      
      <para>
	To list other <application>apt</application> commands and options:
	<screen>apt-get help</screen>
      </para>
      <para>For more information, see the <ulink url="&debian-apt;">Debian <application>apt</application> manual</ulink> and the <ulink url="man:apt-get">apt-get manual</ulink>.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="install-file" status="review">
    <title>Installing a single package file</title>
    <para>
      The preferred method of installing programs is via the package
      managers described in this chapter. However, although the Ubuntu
      package archives are very large, it is possible that you may
      wish to install a package that is not available in the Ubuntu
      archives. If this happens, you can also download and install
      files from websites.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is important to ensure that any files you download come from
      a safe source before installing them.
    </para>
    <para>
      There are many different kinds of Linux package
      files. Most of these are associated with the package
      managers of specific Linux distributions. Examples are
      <emphasis>Debian Package</emphasis> files (<filename
	class="extension">.deb</filename> files),
      <emphasis>RPM Package Manager</emphasis> files
      (<filename class="extension">.rpm</filename> files),
      <emphasis>Tarballs</emphasis> (<filename
	class="extension">.tar</filename> files) and <filename
	class="extension">.run</filename> files.
    </para>
    <para>
      This section deals with installing these single files.
    </para>
    <warning>
      <para>It is not guaranteed that these files will be compatible
	with your system and you will not receive security updates if
	you install these files. For these reasons, if you wish to
	install a program, always use a native Ubuntu package of the
	application available through a package manager, if there is
	one available.
      </para>
    </warning>
    
    <sect2 id="install-deb" status="review">
      <title>Installing/uninstalling <filename class="extension">.deb</filename> files</title>
      <para>
	These files are <emphasis>Debian packages</emphasis>. The
	package files associated with Ubuntu have the <filename
	class="extension">.deb</filename> suffix because of Ubuntu's
	close relations with the Debian GNU/Linux distribution. You
	will need administrative privileges to install a <filename
	class="extension">.deb</filename> file. See <ulink type="help"
	url="ghelp:administrative">Administrative Tasks</ulink> for
	more details.
      </para>
      <para>To install a <filename class="extension">.deb</filename>
	file, double-click on it. If you prefer using the Terminal, enter:
	<screen>sudo dpkg -i <replaceable>package_file.deb</replaceable></screen>
      </para>
      <para>You can use your package manager to uninstall a 
      <filename class="extension">.deb</filename> file once it has been installed. 
      Alternatively, enter the following in a Terminal:
	<screen>sudo dpkg -r <replaceable>package_name</replaceable></screen>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="alien" status="review">
      <title>Converting <filename
	  class="extension">.rpm</filename>
	files to <filename class="extension">.deb</filename> files</title>
      <para>
	Another type of package is the <emphasis>Red Hat Package
	Manager</emphasis> (RPM) file. These have the
	<filename class="extension">.rpm</filename> suffix. It is not recommended to
	install these on an Ubuntu system. In almost all cases, a
	native Ubuntu <filename class="extension">.deb</filename> package is
	available. However, if absolutely necessary, an
	<filename class="extension">.rpm</filename> file can be converted to a
	<filename class="extension">.deb</filename> package using the 
	<application>alien</application> application. The resulting
	<filename class="extension">.deb</filename> file can be installed as
	described above.
      </para>
      <para>To convert an RPM into a <filename class="extension">.deb</filename>:</para>
      <procedure>
	<step>
	  <para>Install the <application>alien</application> package.</para>
	</step>
	<step>
	  <para>
	    In a Terminal, enter:
	    <screen>sudo alien <replaceable>package_file.rpm</replaceable></screen>
	  </para>
	</step>
      </procedure>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="tarballs" status="review">
      <title>Installing <emphasis>tarballs</emphasis></title>
      <para>
	Files with the <filename class="extension">.tar</filename>,
      <filename class="extension">.tgz</filename>, <filename
      class="extension">.tar.gz</filename> or <filename
      class="extension">.tar.bz2</filename> suffix are package files
      known as <emphasis>tarballs</emphasis>, and are widely used in Linux and Unix to 
      package software. Tarballs can also be used to archive and compress other files.</para>
      <para>
	If there is no native Ubuntu package available in any of the Ubuntu repositories, you can use the command line to install or uninstall the tarball file.</para>
      <para>
	The first step will be to uncompress and extract the tarball. If it is a <emphasis>.tgz</emphasis> or a <emphasis>.tar.gz</emphasis>, in a Terminal enter:
	<screen>tar xfvz <replaceable>tarball_name</replaceable></screen>
      </para>
      <para>
	Then it will be necessary to follow the instructions that come
	with the package. These are generally located in the extracted
	tarball in a file called <filename>README</filename> or
	<filename>INSTALL</filename>.
      </para>
      <para>
	Tarballs often contain the source code of the program, and need to be <emphasis>compiled</emphasis> in order to be used.</para>
      <note>
	<para>
	  Compiling programs requires some packages that are not installed by default. You can install most of these all at once by installing the <application>build-essential</application> package.</para></note>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="runpackages" status="review">
      <title>Install <filename class="extension">.run</filename> packages</title>
      <para>Sometimes you may need to install software (most often a game) which has been packaged as a .run file. These files contain the software and a small program to install the software.</para>
      <para>Follow the procedure
	below to install software
	packaged in a <filename class="extension">.run</filename> file:</para>
      <procedure>
	<step><para>Find the <filename class="extension">.run</filename> file in the <application>File Browser</application></para></step>
	<step><para>Right-click the file and select <guilabel>Properties</guilabel></para></step>
	<step><para>Under the <guilabel>Permissions</guilabel> tab, make sure that <guilabel>Allow executing file as program</guilabel> is checked and press <guibutton>Close</guibutton></para></step>
	<step><para>Double-click the <filename class="extension">.run</filename> file and press <guibutton>Run in Terminal</guibutton> to run the installer</para></step>
	<step><para>A <application>Terminal</application> window will open. Follow any instructions on-screen to install the program</para></step>
      </procedure>
      <note>
	<para>Once you have started the installer, it may take a while to display an installation screen. This is normally due to the installer extracting all of the files from the .run file ready for use.</para>
      </note>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</article>
