<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
]>

<?db.chunk.max_depth 2?>
<?yelp:chunk-depth 2?>

<article id="music-video-photos" status="review">
<articleinfo>
    <title>Music, video and photos</title>
    &legalnotice;
</articleinfo>
    <para>
    This section describes how to import, organize and use music, videos and 
    photos with Ubuntu.
    </para>
            
<sect1 id="music" status="review">
    <title>Music and audio</title>
    <para>
    Whether you want to play, rip, edit or organize your music, Ubuntu has the 
    tools that you need.
    </para>
    
    <sect2 id="music-listen" status="review">
        <title>Listen to audio files and CDs</title>
        <para>
        You can use 
        <application>Rhythmbox</application> (&rhythmbox;) and 
        <application>Movie Player</application> (&totem;) to listen to music on 
        your computer.
        </para>
        <para>
        Audio files will be opened in Movie Player when 
        double-clicked, but Rhythmbox is better at handling large music 
        collections.
        </para>
        <para>
        Rhythmbox is also able to play audio CDs, and should open automatically 
        when you insert a CD.
        </para>
        <para>
        See the <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:rhythmbox'>
        Rhythmbox manual</ulink> for more information.
        </para>
        
    <sect3 id="music-cd-autoplay" status="review">
        <title>How can I prevent CDs from playing when I insert them?</title>
        <para>
        Rhythmbox should start playing a CD automatically when you insert it 
        into your CD drive.
        </para>
        <para>
        To prevent this from happening, open your Home folder by clicking 
        &home-folder; on the panel at the top of the screen. Then, click 
        <menuchoice>
            <guimenuitem>Edit</guimenuitem>
            <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
            <guimenuitem>Media</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> and change the <guilabel>CD Audio</guilabel> option to 
        <guilabel>Do Nothing</guilabel>. Finally, press 
        <guibutton>Close</guibutton>.
        </para>
        <para>
        See the <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:user-guide#nautilus-preferences'>
        Nautilus Preferences article</ulink> for more information.
        </para>
    </sect3>
    
    <sect3 id="music-missingmetadata" status="review">
        <title>Song names/cover art are missing/wrong for some songs</title>
        <para>
        Music player applications fetch cover art and other information about 
        songs from the Internet. If song names or cover art are missing, make 
        sure that you are connected to the Internet.
        </para>
        <para>
        Sometimes, your music player may not be able to identify a particular 
        song or album correctly. If this is the case, you can add the correct 
        information manually by using a tag editor such as 
        <ulink url="apt:cowbell">Cowbell</ulink> or 
        <ulink url="apt:easytag-aac">EasyTAG</ulink>. 
        Some music players even have their own tag editor.
        </para>
        <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>
        If only the album cover art is missing for an album:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <procedure>
            <step>
            <para>
            Find a picture of the album cover on the Internet. 
            <ulink url="http://www.amazon.com/">Amazon</ulink> 
            and other music retailers often display pictures of the album 
            cover; right-click it and click 
            <guibutton>Save Image As</guibutton> to save it to your computer.
            </para>
            </step>
            <step>
            <para>
            Rename the picture to <filename>cover.jpg</filename> and copy it 
            into the folder which contains the songs from the album.
            </para>
            </step>
            <step>
            <para>
            Rhythmbox and most other music players should display the correct 
            cover art when a song from the album is next played.
            </para>
            </step>
        </procedure>
        <para>
        Rhythmbox and some other music players allow you to drag a picture onto 
        their cover art display area to change or add cover art for an album.
        </para>
    </sect3>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="music-rip" status="review">
        <title>Copy music from a CD to your computer</title>
        <para>
        You can copy music from a CD to your computer so that you do not have 
        to have the CD in the drive to play songs from it. You can then copy 
        the songs to a digital audio player, such as an iPod.
        </para>
        <para>Applications which perform this task for you are called 
        <emphasis>CD rippers</emphasis> or <emphasis>extractors</emphasis>. 
        The music is often <emphasis>compressed</emphasis> when you copy it, so 
        that it takes up less space on your hard disk. MP3 and WMA files are 
        examples of compressed audio files.
        </para>
        <para>
        Rhythmbox can copy CDs to your computer in a range of different 
        formats. See the <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:rhythmbox#cd-import'>
        Rhythmbox manual</ulink> for instructions. Other applications, such as 
        <ulink type='help' url="ghelp:sound-juicer">Sound Juicer</ulink>, can 
        also be used to extract songs from CDs.
        </para>
        <note>
        <para>
        The <filename>Music</filename> folder is a good place to store your 
        music files when you copy them from a CD; most audio applications look 
        there by default when searching for your music.
        </para>
        </note>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="music-burn" status="review">
        <title>Copy music to a CD</title>
        <para>
        You can create your own audio CDs by copying music from your computer 
        onto a blank disc. CDs that you create in this way should play in any 
        device that can play standard (manufactured) audio CDs. All that is 
        required is a CD burner (also called a CD writer). Most computers have 
        one of these.
        </para>
        <para>
        To begin creating an audio CD, start Brasero (&brasero;) and select 
        <guibutton>Audio project</guibutton> from the main screen. Then, select 
        the songs that you want to add to the CD and add them to the project. 
        Finally, click <guibutton>Burn</guibutton> to copy the songs to a CD.
        </para>
        <para>
        You will also need to select the maximum duration of the CD which you 
        inserted (e.g. 80 minutes), which can be done by clicking on the small 
        CD icon near the bottom of the window. Brasero will warn you if you 
        have selected more files than can fit on the disc.
        </para>
        <para>
        See the <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:brasero'>
        Brasero manual</ulink> for full instructions.
        </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="music-mtp" status="review">
    	<title>MTP Media Players</title>
    	<para>A number of MP3 players, such as those produced by Samsung use 
    	Media Transfer Protocol(MTP). These devices, when used with the correct
    	driver, often appear in Windows as a media device but can be accessed as a USB
    	device.</para>
    	<para>Ubuntu supports these devices but requires two steps:</para>
    	<orderedlist>
    		<listitem><para>Install the <ulink url="apt:mtpfs"><application>mtpfs</application></ulink> 
    		and <ulink url="apt:mtpfs"><application>mtp-tools</application></ulink> packages.</para></listitem>
    		<listitem><para>Open &rhythmbox;.</para></listitem>
    		<listitem><para>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Plugins</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para></listitem>
    		<listitem><para>Tick the <guilabel>Portable Players - MTP</guilabel> plugin.</para></listitem>
    		<listitem><para>Click <guibutton>Close</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
    	</orderedlist>
    	<para>Your device will now be displayed in the left hand pane under <guilabel>Devices</guilabel> 
    	when connected.</para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="music-ipod" status="review">
        <title>Use an iPod or other portable music player</title>
        <para>
        Ubuntu will work with most portable audio players, including iPods. 
        Normally, all you have to do is plug the player into your computer and 
        then use Rhythmbox to copy songs to and from the player. The audio 
        player should appear in the <guilabel>Devices</guilabel> section of the 
        list which is underneath the <guibutton>Play</guibutton> button.
        See the 
        <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:rhythmbox'>Rhythmbox manual</ulink> for 
        more information.
        </para>
        <para>
        If you have a portable music player which can also display photos and 
        videos, you may prefer to use <ulink url="apt:banshee">Banshee</ulink>, 
        which is a music player with good support for such devices. 
        iPod owners may also like to try specialized applications such as 
        <ulink url="apt:gpixpod">GPixPod</ulink> and 
        <ulink url="apt:gtkpod">gtkpod</ulink> for handling multimedia.
        </para>
    
    <sect3 id="music-ipodformat" status="review">
        <title>My portable audio player does not recognize songs copied from 
        Ubuntu</title>
        <para>
        When you copy music from a CD onto a computer, it must be stored in a 
        specific <emphasis>audio format</emphasis>. The default format used by 
        Rhythmbox is Ogg Vorbis (<filename>.ogg</filename> or 
        <filename>.oga</filename>).
        </para>
        <para>
        Not all portable audio players are able to play files in the Ogg Vorbis 
        format; for example, iPods cannot play this format. In order for your 
        player to recognize your songs, you must convert them to a format which 
        it supports. Nearly every player on the market supports the MP3 format, 
        so this is usually a safe bet.
        </para>
        <para>
        You can convert existing audio files to other formats using 
        <ulink url="apt:soundconverter">Sound Converter</ulink>. The output 
        format can be selected in the Sound Converter preferences.
        </para>
        <para>
        You can change the default file format used by Rhythmbox when copying 
        CDs. Click 
        <menuchoice>
            <guimenuitem>Edit</guimenuitem>
            <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
            <guimenuitem>Music</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> 
        and change the <guilabel>Preferred Format</guilabel> to the format of 
        your choice. In future, all CDs copied to your computer will be copied 
        in this format.
        </para>
        <note>
            <para>
            If an MP3 option is not shown in the <guilabel>Preferred Format
            </guilabel> list, <ulink url='apt:gstreamer0.10-plugins-ugly-multiverse'>install the 
            <application>gstreamer0.10-plugins-ugly-multiverse</application> package</ulink> and restart 
            Rhythmbox. The option <guilabel>CD Quality, MP3 (.mp3 type)
            </guilabel> should appear in the <guilabel>Preferred Format
            </guilabel> list.
            </para>
        </note>
    </sect3>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="music-podcasts" status="review">
        <title>Listen to podcasts and Internet radio stations</title>
        <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>Podcasts</emphasis> are pre-recorded shows 
        which you can download and listen to on your computer or portable audio 
        player. Thousands of podcasts are available and most can be downloaded 
        for free.
        </para>
        <para>
        You can use Rhythmbox to download and play podcasts; select 
        <guilabel>Podcasts</guilabel> from the <guilabel>Library</guilabel> 
        section of the Rhythmbox window to get started. The 
        <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:rhythmbox'>Rhythmbox manual</ulink> has 
        further instructions. Alternatively, you may prefer to use a dedicated 
        podcast manager such as <ulink url="apt:gpodder">gPodder</ulink> or 
        <ulink url="apt:penguintv">PenguinTV</ulink>.
        </para>
        <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>Internet radio stations</emphasis> are live 
        <emphasis>audio streams</emphasis>, similar to standard radio but 
        transmitted over the Internet. You can use Rhythmbox to listen to 
        Internet radio too; select <guilabel>Radio</guilabel> from the 
        <guilabel>Library</guilabel> section of the Rhythmbox window to get 
        started and see the 
        <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:rhythmbox'>Rhythmbox manual</ulink> for 
        more details.
        </para>
        <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>RealAudio streams</emphasis>, as used by some 
        Internet radio stations, are not supported by Rhythmbox. To listen to 
        this type of stream, <link linkend="video-realplayer">
        install RealPlayer</link>.
        </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="music-download" status="review">
        <title>Download music from the Internet</title>
        <para>
        Many websites which allow you to buy music online and download it onto 
        your computer are designed to work with Microsoft Windows only. As a 
        result, some services will not work with Ubuntu.
        </para>
        <para>
        Ubuntu is able to play most audio formats, including MP3, WMA and AAC. 
        However, it does not support the various DRM (Digital Rights 
        Management) schemes which stores sometimes use to restrict access to 
        their music. If you download audio files which are DRM-restricted, they 
        are unlikely to work in Ubuntu. In particular, nearly all music from 
        the iTunes music store is DRM-restricted and so cannot be played.
        </para>
        <para>
        Two services which offer unrestricted (DRM-free) music are 
        <ulink url="http://www.jamendo.com">Jamendo</ulink> and 
        <ulink url="">Magnatune</ulink>. You can buy songs from both of these 
        stores online, or directly from within Rhythmbox if the appropriate 
        plugins are enabled (see the <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:rhythmbox'>
        Rhythmbox manual</ulink> for more information).
        </para>
        <caution>
            <para>
            Downloading music from the Internet without the permission of its 
            copyright holder is considered illegal in many countries. You 
            should check that you are within your rights to download a music 
            file before saving it onto your computer.
            </para>
        </caution>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="music-recording" status="review">
        <title>Recording sounds</title>
        <para>
        You can record sounds onto your computer if you have a microphone or 
        other recording equipment connected to it.
        </para>
        <para>
        To start a basic sound recording application, press 
        <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo>, 
        type <userinput>gnome-sound-recorder</userinput> into the text box and 
        then click <guibutton>Run</guibutton>. See the 
        <ulink type='help' url="ghelp:gnome-sound-recorder">
        Sound Recorder manual</ulink> for instructions on how to use it.
        </para>
        <para>
        For more advanced recording needs, you may like to try a multi-track 
        audio editor such as 
        <ulink url="apt:jokosher">Jokosher</ulink> or 
        <ulink url="apt:audacity">Audacity</ulink>.
        </para>
        <para>
        Many other professional-level recording tools are available for Ubuntu. 
        See the <ulink url="http://ubuntustudio.org/">
        Ubuntu Studio website</ulink> for more information.
        </para>
    
    <sect3 id="music-microphone" status="review">
        <title>My microphone does not work or is too quiet</title>
        <para>
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role='strong'>
                    Check that the microphone is connected to the correct socket
                    </emphasis>
                </para>
                <para>
                Most computers have three or more similar-looking audio 
                sockets, so you should check that the microphone is plugged 
                into the correct one. It is usually colored pink and has a 
                microphone icon next to it.
                </para>
                <para>
                In some rare cases, sockets do not work as labeled. For 
                example, your microphone socket may act as the 
                <quote>Line Out</quote> socket and vice versa. If this is the 
                case, use trial and error to find the correct microphone socket.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role='strong'>
                    Check that the microphone is not muted in the settings
                    </emphasis>
                </para>
                <para>
                The microphone input may have been muted or its volume reduced 
                in the system settings.
                </para>
                <procedure>
                    <step>
                    <para>
                    Right-click the speaker icon on the panel at the top of 
                    your screen and select 
                    <guilabel>Open Volume Control</guilabel>. If you do not 
                    have a speaker icon on your panel, press 
                    <keycombo>
                        <keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F2</keycap>
                    </keycombo>, type 
                    <userinput>gnome-volume-control</userinput> and click 
                    <guibutton>Run</guibutton> instead.
                    </para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                    <para>
                    When the Volume Control opens, click 
                    <menuchoice>
                        <guimenuitem>Edit</guimenuitem>
                        <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
                    </menuchoice> 
                    and make sure that all of the items related to the 
                    microphone settings are checked. Click 
                    <guibutton>Close</guibutton> to return to the volume 
                    control.
                    </para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                    <para>
                    Under the <guilabel>Playback</guilabel> tab, make sure that 
                    all of the microphone settings are unmuted and that their 
                    volume is set high enough. If a microphone is muted, a 
                    speaker icon with a red cross over it will be displayed 
                    underneath its volume slider; click that icon to unmute the 
                    microphone.
                    </para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                    <para>
                    You may also find it necessary to change other settings to 
                    get your microphone to work properly. For example, the 
                    <guilabel>Mic Boost</guilabel> and 
                    <guilabel>External Amplifier</guilabel> settings under the 
                    <guilabel>Switches</guilabel> tab and the 
                    <guilabel>Mic Select</guilabel> setting under the 
                    <guilabel>Options</guilabel> tab can all affect the volume 
                    of your microphone.
                    </para>
                    </step>
                </procedure>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role='strong'>
                    Check the volume control on the microphone
                    </emphasis>
                </para>
                <para>
                Some microphones have an integrated volume control. Check that 
                the volume control on your microphone is turned up.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role='strong'>
                    Check the volume control in the recording application
                    </emphasis>
                </para>
                <para>
                Some applications allow you to change the volume of the 
                microphone from within the application. Check the volume 
                settings in the application that you are using.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect3>
    </sect2>
</sect1>
    
<sect1 id="video" status="review">
    <title>Movies, DVDs and videos</title>
    <para>
    You can watch movies and video clips with the 
    <application>Totem Movie Player</application> (&totem;).
    </para>
    
    <sect2 id="video-dvd" status="review">
        <title>Playing DVDs</title>
        <para>
        In order to play DVDs you must install some additional software. 
        Unfortunately, DVD support cannot be provided by default in Ubuntu due 
        to legal restrictions in some countries.
        </para>
        <warning>
        <para>
        Read about <ulink url='ghelp:add-applications#restricted-software'>
        restricted formats</ulink> before following the instructions below. 
        There are some legal issues that you should be aware of.
        </para>
        </warning>
        <procedure>
            <step>
            <para>
            Install the 
            <ulink url='apt:libdvdnav4'>libdvdnav4</ulink>, 
            <ulink url='apt:libdvdread3'>libdvdread3</ulink> and 
            <ulink url='apt:gstreamer0.10-plugins-ugly'>
            gstreamer0.10-plugins-ugly</ulink> packages.
            </para>
            </step>
            <step>
            <para>
            If you would like to play encrypted DVDs, press &terminal; and type 
            the following into the screen which appears, followed by the 
            <keycap>Enter</keycap> key: 
            <screen>sudo /usr/share/doc/libdvdread3/install-css.sh</screen>
            </para>
            </step>
            <step>
            <para>
            Enter your password if prompted. The 
            <application>libdvdcss2</application> package will be downloaded 
            and installed from a website.
            </para>
            </step>
            <step>
            <para>
            Insert a DVD into your drive. It should open automatically in the 
            Movie Player.
            </para>
            </step>
        </procedure>
    
    <sect3 id="video-dvdmenus" status="review">
        <title>Where have the menus on my DVDs gone?</title>
        <para>
        DVD menus are not currently supported by the default Movie Player. To 
        be able to use the menus on a disc, you must install an alternative 
        movie player such as <ulink url="apt:gxine">gxine</ulink> or 
        <ulink url="apt:vlc">VLC</ulink>.
        </para>
        <para>
        To make DVDs automatically play in the alternative movie player when 
        inserted, open &home-folder;, click 
        <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> and then click the <guilabel>Media</guilabel> tab. 
        Select the alternative player from the <guibutton>DVD Video</guibutton> 
        list.
        </para>
    </sect3>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="video-playback" status="review">
        <title>How can I get my videos to play?</title>
        
        <para>
        Some video formats, such as Flash, QuickTime, and Windows Media Video, 
        are proprietary and so support for them cannot be included in Ubuntu by 
        default. You must install some extra software to allow playback.
        </para>
        <para>In order to play the most common proprietary formats in the 
        Totem movie player or Firefox web browser, <ulink url='apt:ubuntu-restricted-extras'>install the 
        ubuntu-restricted-extras package</ulink> (see 
        <ulink url='ghelp:add-applications#restricted-software'>Restricted 
        Software</ulink> for more information).
        </para>
        
        <sect3 id="video-playback-file" status="review">
        <title>Video files</title>
        <para>
        <emphasis>(e.g. QuickTime, Windows Media)</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para>
        If you try to play an unsupported video file, you will be asked if you 
        would like to <guilabel>search for a suitable codec</guilabel>. Click 
        <guibutton>Search</guibutton> and, when the <guilabel>Install 
        multimedia codecs</guilabel> window appears, select one of the codecs 
        displayed in the list and click <guibutton>Install</guibutton>.
        </para>
        <para>
        If you are asked to <guilabel>confirm installation of restricted 
        software</guilabel>, the codec required to play your video may have 
        some <ulink url='ghelp:add-applications#restricted-software'>legal 
        restrictions</ulink> which you should be aware of. If you think that 
        the restrictions do not apply to you, press 
        <guibutton>Confirm</guibutton> to continue with the installation.
        </para>
        <para>
        Once installation is complete, the video should begin to play. If not, 
        try closing and then re-opening the video.
        </para>
        </sect3>
        
        <sect3 id="video-playback-flash" status="review">
        <title>Flash videos</title>
        <para>
        <emphasis>(e.g. Youtube, iPlayer)</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para>
        When you first try to play a Flash video in the Firefox web browser, a 
        bar will appear at the top of the window saying that 
        <guilabel>additional plugins are required</guilabel>. Press the 
        <guibutton>Install Missing Plugins</guibutton> button and follow the 
        instructions on-screen to install a Flash player.
        </para>
        <para>
        You will be offered the choice of several players. The 
        <guilabel>Adobe Flash Player</guilabel> is the official plugin, which 
        should offer the best support for videos. Unfortunately, it is 
        proprietary software and so cannot be supported directly by Ubuntu. 
        The Swfdec and Gnash players are not proprietary and so are supported. 
        You may also find them to be more stable (cause fewer problems) than 
        the official player.
        </para>
        </sect3>
        
        <sect3 id="video-playback-streaming" status="review">
        <title>Streaming video</title>
        <para>
        <emphasis>(e.g. RealVideo)</emphasis>
        </para>
        <para>
        The most reliable way of playing RealVideo-format videos is to install 
        the official RealPlayer software. See <link linkend="video-realplayer">
        Installing and configuring RealPlayer</link> for full instructions.
        </para>
        <para>
        Support for most other types of streaming video can be added by 
        following the instructions for 
        <link linkend="video-playback-file">video files</link> or 
        <link linkend="video-playback-flash">Flash videos</link>. If you are 
        having difficulties getting a video to stream in your web browser, 
        right-click the video and select 
        <guilabel>Open with "Movie Player"</guilabel> if that option is 
        available.
        </para>
        </sect3>
        
        <sect3 id="video-playback-unsupported" status="review">
        <title>Videos that are otherwise unsupported</title>
        <para>
        If none of the other instructions in this section work with a 
        particular video, try using a different media player. 
        <ulink url='apt:vlc'>VLC</ulink> and 
        <ulink url='apt:mplayer'>MPlayer</ulink> support a wide range of 
        formats; it is recommended that you try one of these.
        </para>
        </sect3>
        
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="video-realplayer" status="review">
        <title>Installing and configuring RealPlayer</title>
        <para>
        RealPlayer is a proprietary application, and so is not installed in the 
        usual way.
        </para>
        <procedure>
        <step>
            <para>
            Download a suitable Linux installer from the 
            <ulink url='http://uk.real.com/player/select/'>
            RealPlayer website</ulink> and save it in your Home folder.
            </para>
        </step>
        <step>
            <para>
            Open a Terminal (&terminal;) and type the following, pressing 
            <keycap>Enter</keycap> at the end of each line and typing your 
            password when prompted:
            </para>
            <screen>
sudo chmod a+x RealPlayer*
sudo ./RealPlayer*</screen>
        </step>
        <step>
            <para>
            You should see the text <guilabel>Extracting files for Helix 
            installation</guilabel> on the screen if the installer has started 
            properly. When asked a question by the installer, press 
            <keycap>Enter</keycap> to accept the default.
            </para>
        </step>
        <step>
            <para>
            When the installer has finished copying files, press &realplayer; 
            and follow the instructions on the screen to complete set-up.
            </para>
        </step>
        </procedure>
        
        <para>
         For more in-depth instructions, see the <ulink 
         url='https://help.ubuntu.com/community/RealPlayerInstallationMethods'>
         community help wiki</ulink>.
        </para>
        
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="video-editing" status="review">
        <title>Recording and editing video</title>
        <para>
        There are numerous video capture and editing programs available for 
        Ubuntu. Some of the most popular include 
        <ulink url="apt:kino">Kino</ulink>, 
        <ulink url="apt:kdenlive">Kdenlive</ulink>, and 
        <ulink url="apt:pitivi">Pitivi</ulink>.
        </para>
    </sect2>
    
</sect1>


<!--<sect1 id="codecs" status="review">
    <title>What is a codec?</title>
    <para>
    A <emphasis>multimedia codec</emphasis> is a small piece of software which 
    allows you to watch videos or listen to music of a specific format. There 
    are many different multimedia formats and so you may need to install 
    several codecs. Ubuntu includes many codecs by default.
    </para>
    <para>
    Many applications in Ubuntu use the <application>GStreamer</application> 
    open source multimedia framework. The codec plugins for 
    <application>GStreamer</application> are organised in different packages 
    depending on the licensing that applies to the various codecs. You can see 
    which codecs are contained in which plugin on the 
    <ulink url="http://gstreamer.freedesktop.org/documentation/plugins.html">
    GStreamer website</ulink>.
    </para>
    
    <warning>
        <para>
        In some countries, the use of certain codecs may be prohibited by law. 
        You should verify that you are permitted to use them before installing 
        them.
        </para>
    </warning>
</sect1>
-->

<sect1 id="photos" status="review">
    <title>Photos and cameras</title>
    <para>
    There are many tools available to help you to work with your digital photo 
    collection.
    </para>
    
    <sect2 id="photos-import" status="review">
        <title>Import photos from a digital camera</title>
        <para>
        Ubuntu automatically detects most digital cameras when you plug them 
        in, and will offer to import your photos automatically.
        </para>
        <para>
        To import photos from your camera:
        </para>
        <procedure>
            <step>
            <para>
            Plug-in and switch on the camera by placing it in review mode. 
            Ubuntu should ask you if you would like to import the photos that 
            the camera contains.
            </para>
            </step>
            <step>
            <para>
            Click on <guibutton>Import</guibutton>. You should then see a 
            preview of the photos.
            </para>
            </step>
            <step>
            <para>
            Choose a location to save your photos to, then click on 
            <guibutton>Import</guibutton>. The photos will be saved to your 
            hard drive.
            </para>
            </step>
        </procedure>
        
        <para>
        If Ubuntu does not ask you if it can import the photos:
        </para>
        <procedure>
            <step>
            <para>
            Open &f-spot; and choose 
            <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>File</guimenu>
                <guimenuitem>Import</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>.
            </para>
            </step>
            <step>
            <para>
            Select your camera as the <guilabel>Import Source</guilabel> and 
            then click <guibutton>Import</guibutton> to begin importing your 
            photos.
            </para>
            </step>
        </procedure>
        <para>
        If your camera does not appear as an import source, press &computer; 
        and check if your camera is visible there as a removable storage 
        device. If it is, you can then copy the photos manually using the 
        <application>File Browser</application>.
        </para>
        
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="photos-organize" status="review">
        <title>Organize your photo collection</title>
        <para>
        <application>F-Spot</application> provides a complete solution for 
        managing your photo collection. To start it, choose &f-spot;.
        </para>
        <para>
        With <application>F-Spot</application>, you can import photos from your 
        digital camera or USB stick, tag them with familiar terms, do touch 
        ups, and edit them in different ways. In addition to this, you can 
        upload photos easily to your Flickr, PicasaWeb album and other online 
        photo galleries.
        </para>
        <para>
        For help with <application>F-Spot Photo Manager</application>, see the 
        <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:f-spot">F-Spot User Guide</ulink>.
        </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2 id="photos-slideshow" status="review">
        <title>Watch a slideshow of photos</title>    
        <para>
        If you want to show off your photos in all of their glory, why not run 
        a slideshow of them?
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
            <para>
            Watch a slideshow using the 
            <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:eog#eog-fullscreen'>
            Image Viewer</ulink>
            </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
            <para>
            Watch a slideshow using the <ulink type='help' 
            url='ghelp:f-spot#enjoying-fullscreen-mode-and-slideshows'>
            F-Spot Photo Manager</ulink>
            </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        <sect3 id="photos-slideshow-screensaver" status="review">
            <title>Setting a Slideshow as Your Screensaver</title>
            <para>
            You can use a slideshow of your photos as you screensaver:
            </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                Press &screensaver;
                </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                Select the <guilabel>F-Spot photos</guilabel> screensaver 
                theme
                </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                Photos which are tagged as <guilabel>Favorites</guilabel> in 
                <application>F-Spot Photo Manager</application> will be 
                displayed as your screensaver
                </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            
            <para>
            If you would like to change which tag is used for the slideshow:
            </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                Open F-Spot
                </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                Press 
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenuitem>Edit</guimenuitem>
                    <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>
                </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para>Under <guilabel>Screensaver</guilabel>, select the 
                desired tag
                </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para>Press <guibutton>Close</guibutton>
                </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="photos-printing" status="review">
        <title>Printing photos</title>
        <para>
        Printing your photos is great way to share them with others.
        </para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
            <para>
            Double-click the photo you want to print to open it in the 
            <application>Image Viewer</application>
            </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
            <para>Press 
            <menuchoice>
                <guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem>
                <guimenuitem>Page Setup</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                Under <guilabel>Format for</guilabel>, select the printer which 
                you are going to use
                </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                Under <guilabel>Paper size</guilabel>, select the size of the 
                paper which you are going to print the photo onto
                </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                Under <guilabel>Orientation</guilabel>, choose the orientation 
                of the photo on the paper
                </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
            <para>
            Press <guibutton>Apply</guibutton>
            </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
            <para>
            Press 
            <menuchoice>
                <guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem>
                <guimenuitem>Print</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
            <para>
            Change any settings as appropriate (see below)
            </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
            <para>
            Press <guibutton>Print</guibutton> to print the photo
            </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <sect3 id="photos-printing-settings" status="review">
            <title>Printer Settings</title>
            <para>
            You can tweak your printing settings to get the best results. All 
            of these settings can be found in the 
            <menuchoice>
                <guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem>
                <guimenuitem>Print</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice> 
            window.
            </para>
            <para>
            Make sure that you select your printer from the list on the 
            <guilabel>General</guilabel> tab to get the full range of settings 
            supported by your printer.
            </para>
            <note>
                <para>
                Different makes of printer will have different printer 
                settings. The settings below are only provided as a guide for 
                what you may be able to change with your particular printer.
                </para>
            </note>

            <sect4 id="photos-printing-paper" status="review">
                <title>Paper Type</title>
                <para>
                The paper type that you use has a large impact on the quality 
                of your printed photo. You should set the paper type to match 
                the paper which you are using in your printer to prevent poor 
                results. Using a <emphasis>glossy</emphasis> paper type with 
                only <emphasis>plain</emphasis> paper loaded into your printer 
                will generally produce poor results, for example.
                </para>
                <para>
                This setting may automatically change the amount of ink which 
                is used, in order to get the best results and to prevent 
                smudging. How this is handled will depend on your printer.
                </para>
            </sect4>

            <sect4 id="photos-printing-quality" status="review">
                <title>Print Quality</title>
                <para>
                Print quality is generally measured in <emphasis>DPI</emphasis> 
                (dots per inch). A greater DPI value should result in better 
                print quality.
                </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                    Choose <guilabel>Draft</guilabel> for making quick draft 
                    prints which don't use much ink
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                    <para>
                    Choose <guilabel>Best Quality</guilabel> or 
                    <guilabel>Photo</guilabel> for making high quality prints. 
                    Printing will be slower and will use more ink
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </sect4>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="photos-printing-advanced" status="review">
            <title>Advanced Photo Printing</title>
            <para>
            For advanced photo printing, <ulink url="apt:photoprint">install the 
            <application>PhotoPrint</application> package</ulink>
	    from the universe repository. Once 
            installed, press &photoprint; to start PhotoPrint.
            </para>
            <para>
            PhotoPrint allows you to fine-tune your printing settings.
            </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                Under <guilabel>Page Size</guilabel>, change the page size to 
                the size of paper that you want to print onto.
                </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                Under <guilabel>Layout</guilabel>, change the number of columns 
                and rows to reflect the number of photos that you want to put 
                onto a page
                </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                To change the amount of spacing between photos, change the 
                <guilabel>Horizontal</guilabel> and 
                <guilabel>Vertical</guilabel> settings under 
                <guilabel>Gutters</guilabel>
                </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                To add a photo to the page, press 
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenuitem>Image</guimenuitem>
                    <guimenuitem>Add Image</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice> and select a photo
                </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                To change the advanced printer settings, press 
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem>
                    <guimenuitem>Print Setup</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>
                </para>
                <para>
                You may need to select the correct printer model on the 
                <guilabel>Output</guilabel> tab
                </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                Press 
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem>
                    <guimenuitem>Print</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice> to print your photos
                </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="photos-sharing" status="review">
        <title>Sharing your photos</title>
        <para>
        If you want to share your collection of photos with others, why not use 
        an online photo sharing service or burn a CD of your photos? Ubuntu has 
        plenty of tools to help you share your pictures.
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
            <para>
            <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:musicvideophotos#photos-printing'>
            Print copies</ulink> of your photos.
            </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
            <para>
            Share your photos over the Internet using a <ulink type='help' 
            url='ghelp:f-spot#sharing-flickr-or-php-gallery'>
            photo sharing service</ulink> or a <ulink type='help' 
            url='ghelp:f-spot#website-gallery-folder'>web gallery</ulink>.
            </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
            <para>
            Burn a CD of your photos using the 
            <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:musicvideophotos#cdburning'>
            File Browser</ulink> or 
            <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:f-spot#sharing-burn-to-cd'>
            F-Spot Photo Manager</ulink>.
            </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
            <para>
            Present a 
            <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:musicvideophotos#photos-slideshow'>
            slideshow</ulink> of your photos.
            </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
            <para>
            <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:f-spot#sharing-e-mail'>
            E-mail copies</ulink> of your photos directly.
            </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="photos-editing" status="review">
        <title>Edit and improve photos</title>
        <para>
        Sometimes, you may need to adjust or touch-up a photo to make it look 
        better or to remove some flaw. <application>F-Spot</application> 
        includes a few basic tools for doing this. To access these tools, press 
        the <guibutton>Edit Photo</guibutton> button and then click on one of 
        the tools at the bottom of the screen.
        </para>
        <para>
        The <application>GIMP Image Editor</application> is much more advanced. 
        It is installed in Ubuntu by default, and can be started by choosing 
        &gimp;.
        </para>
        <para>
        The GIMP has many professional-level features. It includes tools for 
        selections, drawing, creating paths, masks, filters, effects, and more.
        </para>
    
        <sect3 id="photos-rotating" status="review">
            <title>Rotating photos</title>
            <para>
            You may find that you have some photos which are the wrong way up. 
            It is easy to rotate photos so that they're the right way up again.
            </para>
            <para>
            The <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:eog#eog-manipulate'>
            Image Viewer</ulink>, F-Spot Photo Manager and the GIMP Image 
            Editor are all capable of rotating photos.
            </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="photos-resizing" status="review">
            <title>Resizing photos</title>
            <para>
            You can resize photos which are too big. If you have a photo which 
            has a large file size, resizing it will also reduce the file size.
            </para>
            <para>
            The <application>GIMP Image Editor</application> supports several 
            methods of resizing photos. We will concentrate on the simplest 
            method.
            </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                Open the photo you want to resize in the GIMP Image Editor
                </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                Press 
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenuitem>Image</guimenuitem>
                    <guimenuitem>Scale Image</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>
                </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                Adjust the <guilabel>Width</guilabel> or 
                <guilabel>Height</guilabel> as appropriate. The image will be 
                kept to scale.
                </para>
                <para>
                If you want to adjust the width and height independently, press 
                the link button which connects the <guilabel>Width</guilabel> 
                and <guilabel>Height</guilabel> boxes, so that it looks like a 
                broken link.
                </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                Under <guilabel>Quality</guilabel>, change the 
                <guilabel>Interpolation</guilabel> to 
                <guilabel>Cubic (Best)</guilabel>. This will give you the best 
                quality resized image
                </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                Press <guilabel>Scale</guilabel> to resize the photo
                </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                Press 
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem>
                    <guimenuitem>Save As</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice> and choose a new filename for the photo
                </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                Press <guilabel>Save</guilabel> to save the resized photo
                </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </sect3>
    </sect2>
</sect1>
    
<sect1 id="cdburning" status="review">
    <title>Burning CDs and DVDs</title>
    <para>
    You can make your own CDs by <emphasis>burning</emphasis> files onto a 
    blank disc using the <emphasis>CD writer drive</emphasis> of your computer.
    </para>
    <para>
    Use the Brasero Disc Burning software to create data, audio and video CDs, 
    copy CDs and DVDs and create CDs from disc image files. Click &brasero; to 
    start Brasero.
    </para>
    <para>
    For help and instructions, open Brasero and click 
    <menuchoice>
     <guimenuitem>Help</guimenuitem>
     <guimenuitem>Contents</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice> to view a full manual.
    </para>
</sect1>

</article>
