<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../ubuntu/libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
	<chapter>
		<title>Basic Concepts</title>
				<para>Linux is inspired by the Unix operating system which first appeared in 1969, and has been in continous use and development ever since. Many of the design conventions behind Unix also exist in Linux and are central to understanding the basics of the system.
				</para>
				<para>Unix was primarily oriented towards the command line interface, and that legacy is carried on in Linux. Thus, the graphical user interface with its windows, icons and menus are built on top of a basic command line interface. Furthermore, this means that the Linux file system is structured to be easily manageable and accessible from the command line.
				</para>
		<sect1 id="directories-file-systems" status="complete">
			<title>Directories and File Systems</title>
				<para>Linux and Unix file systems are organised in a hierarchical, tree-like structure.  The highest level of the file system is the <filename>/</filename> or <emphasis>root directory</emphasis>.  In the Unix and Linux design philosophy, everything is considered a file - including hard disks, partitions and removable media. This means that all files and directories (including other disks and partitions) exist under the root directory.
				</para>
				<para>For example, <filename>/home/jebediah/cheeses.odt</filename> shows the correct full path to the <filename>cheeses.odt</filename> file that exists in the <filename>jebediah</filename> directory which is under the <filename>home</filename> directory, which in turn, is under the root (<filename>/</filename>) directory.
				</para>
				<para>Underneath the root (<filename>/</filename>) directory, there is a set of important system directories that are commonly used across most Linux distributions.  The following is a listing of common directories that are directly under the root (<filename>/</filename>) directory:
				</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para><filename>/bin</filename> - important <emphasis>bin</emphasis>ary applications
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><filename>/boot</filename> - files that are required to <emphasis>boot</emphasis> the computer
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><filename>/dev</filename> - the <emphasis>dev</emphasis>ice files
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><filename>/etc</filename> - configuration files, startup scripts, <emphasis>etc</emphasis>...
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><filename>/home</filename> - local users' <emphasis>home</emphasis> directories
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><filename>/lib</filename> - system <emphasis>lib</emphasis>raries
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><filename>/lost+found</filename> - provides a <emphasis>lost+found</emphasis> system for files that exist under the root (<filename>/</filename>) directory
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><filename>/media</filename> - mounted (loaded) removable <emphasis>media</emphasis> such as CDs, digital cameras, etc...
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><filename>/mnt</filename> - <emphasis>m</emphasis>ou<emphasis>nt</emphasis>ed filesystems
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><filename>/opt</filename> - provides a location for <emphasis>opt</emphasis>ional applications to be installed
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><filename>/proc</filename> - special dynamic directory that maintains information about the state of the system, including currently running <emphasis>proc</emphasis>esses
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><filename>/root</filename> - <emphasis>root</emphasis> user home directory, pronounced &apos;slash-root&apos;
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><filename>/sbin</filename> - important <emphasis>s</emphasis>ystem <emphasis>bin</emphasis>aries
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><filename>/srv</filename> - provides a location for data used by <emphasis>s</emphasis>e<emphasis>rv</emphasis>ers</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><filename>/sys</filename> - contains information about the <emphasis>sys</emphasis>tem
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><filename>/tmp</filename> - <emphasis>t</emphasis>e<emphasis>mp</emphasis>orary files
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><filename>/usr</filename> - applications and files that are mostly available for all <emphasis>us</emphasis>e<emphasis>r</emphasis>s to access
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><filename>/var</filename> - <emphasis>var</emphasis>iable files such as logs and databases
							</para>
						</listitem> 
					</itemizedlist>
		</sect1>

		<sect1 id="permissions" status="review">
			<title>Permissions</title>
                       <para>All of the files on a Linux system have permissions that allow or prevent others from viewing, modifying or executing them. The super user "root" has the ability to access any file on the system. Each file has access restrictions, user restrictions and have an owner/group association.
                       </para>
                       <para>Every file is secured by the following three sets of permissions:
                       </para>
                       <itemizedlist>
                         <listitem>
                           <para><emphasis>user</emphasis></para>
                           <para>applies to the user who is the owner of the file</para>
                         </listitem>
                         <listitem>
                           <para><emphasis>group</emphasis></para>
                           <para>applies to the group that is associated with the file</para>
                         </listitem>
                         <listitem>
                           <para><emphasis>other</emphasis></para>
                           <para>applies to all other users</para>
                         </listitem>
                       </itemizedlist>
                       <para>Inside each of the three sets of permissions are the actual permissons.  The permissions, along with the way they apply differently to files and directories, are outlined below:
                       </para>
                       <itemizedlist>
                         <listitem>
                           <para><emphasis>read</emphasis></para>
                           <para>files can be displayed/opened</para>
                           <para>directory contents can be displayed</para>
                         </listitem>
                         <listitem>
                           <para><emphasis>write</emphasis></para>
                           <para>files can be edited or deleted</para>
                           <para>directory contents can be modified</para>
                         </listitem>
                         <listitem>
                           <para><emphasis>execute</emphasis></para>
                           <para>executable files can be run as a program</para>
                           <para>directories can be entered</para>
                         </listitem>
                       </itemizedlist>
				<para>To view and edit the permissions on files and directories, open the <phrase>&home-folder;</phrase> and right-click on a file or directory. Then select <guimenu>Properties</guimenu>.  The permissions exist under the <guilabel>Permissions</guilabel> tab and allow for the editing of all permission levels, if you are the owner of the file.
				</para>
				<para>To learn more about file permissions in Linux, read the <ulink url="&wiki-filepermissions;">file permissions page</ulink> in the Ubuntu Wiki.
				</para>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 id="terminals" status="review">
		<title>Terminals</title>
            <para>Working at the command line is not as daunting a task
                as you would think. There is no special knowledge needed to know
                how to use the command line, it is a program like everything
                else. Most things in Linux can be done using the command line,
                although there are graphical tools for most programs, sometimes
                they are just not enough. This is where the command line comes
                in handy.
				</para>
    	      <para>The terminal is often called the command prompt
		    or the shell.  In days gone by, this was the way the
                    user interacted with the computer, however Linux users have
                    found that the use of the shell can be quicker than a
                    graphical method and still holds some merit today. Here you
                    will learn how to use the terminal.
				</para>
				<para>The original use of the terminal was a file browser and
                    indeed it is still used as a file browser, in the event of
                    the graphical environment failing.  You can use the terminal
                    as a file browser to navigate your files and undo the
                    changes that have been made.
				</para>
		<sect2 id="starting-a-terminal" status="review">
			<title>Starting the Terminal</title>
				<para>To start <application>Terminal</application> choose &terminal;.
				</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="common-commands" status="review">
			<title>Common Commands</title>
				<variablelist>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>View Directories - ls
						</term>
							<listitem><para>The <application>ls</application> (LiSt) lists files in different colors with full formatted text</para></listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>Create Directories - mkdir (directory name)
						</term>
							<listitem><para>The <application>mkdir</application> (MaKeDIRectory) command will create a directory.</para></listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
		    			<term>Change Directories - cd (/directory/location)
		    			</term>
		    				<listitem><para>The <application>cd</application> (ChangeDirectory) command will change from your current directory to any directory you specify.</para>
		    				</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
		    		<varlistentry>
		    			<term>Copy Files/Directories - cp (file or directory name) (to directory or filename)
		    			</term>
		    				<listitem><para>The <application>cp</application> (CoPy) command will copy any files you specify. The <application>cp -r</application> command will copy any directories you specify.</para>
		    				</listitem>
		    		</varlistentry>
		    		<varlistentry>
		    			<term>Remove Files/Directories - rm (file or directory name)</term>
	            		<listitem><para>The <application>rm</application> (ReMove) command will delete any filename you specify. The <application>rm -rf</application> command will remove any directory you specify.</para></listitem>
					</varlistentry>
		    		<varlistentry>
		    			<term>Rename Files/Directories - mv (file or directory name)</term>
							<listitem><para>The <application>mv</application> (MoVe) command will rename/move any file or directory you specify.</para>
		    				</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>Find Files/Directories - locate (file or directory name)</term>
							<listitem><para>The <application>locate</application> command will search your computer for any filename you specify. It uses an index of the files on your system to work quickly: to update this index run the command <application>updatedb</application>. This command is run automatically each day, if you leave your computer on. It needs to be run with administrative privileges (see <xref linkend="root-and-sudo"/>).</para>
							</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					</variablelist>
			<para>You can also use wildcards to match one or more files, such as "*" (for all files) or "?" 
		    (to match one character).
			</para>
			<para>For a more thorough introduction to the Linux command line, please read the <ulink url="&wiki-BasicCommands;">command line introduction</ulink> on the Ubuntu wiki.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 status="complete">
			<title>Switching to Console mode</title>
				<para>The usual method of command-line access in Ubuntu is to start a terminal (see <xref linkend="starting-a-terminal"/> above) 
			, however sometimes it is useful to switch to the real console:</para>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>Use the <keycombo>
								<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
								<keycap>Alt</keycap>
								<keycap>F1</keycap>
							</keycombo>
							shortcut keys to switch to the first console.
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>To switch back to Desktop mode, use the <keycombo>
								<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
								<keycap>Alt</keycap>
								<keycap>F7</keycap>
							</keycombo> shortcut keys.
						</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
					<note>
						<para>There are six consoles available. Each one is accessible with the
							shortcut keys <keycombo>
								<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
								<keycap>Alt</keycap>
								<keycap>F1</keycap>
							</keycombo> to <keycombo>
								<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
								<keycap>Alt</keycap>
								<keycap>F6</keycap>
							</keycombo>.
						</para>
					</note>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 status="review">
			<title>Disabling the beep sound in Terminal mode</title>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>
						Start a <application>Terminal</application>
						session,
						select: <phrase>&terminal;</phrase>
						from the desktop menu system. 
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							<menuchoice>
								<guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
								<guimenuitem>Current Profile...</guimenuitem>
							</menuchoice>
							. Select the
							<guibutton>General</guibutton> tab. Uncheck the
							<guilabel>Terminal bell</guilabel>
							checkbox.
						</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="text-editing" status="review">
  			<title>Text Editing</title>
 			<para>All of the configurations and settings in Linux are saved in text files. Even though you most often can edit configurations through the graphical interface, you may occasionally have to edit them by hand. <application>Gedit</application> is the default Ubuntu text editor, which you can launch by clicking &text-editor; on the desktop menu system.
 			</para>
 			<para>At times in this guide, <application>Gedit</application> is run from the command line using <application>gksudo</application>, which runs <application>Gedit</application> with administrative privileges, in order to modify configuration files.
 			</para>
			<para>If you need to use a text editor from the command line, you can use <application>nano</application>, which is a simple to use text editor. When running it from the command line, always use the following command, which ensures that the editor will not introduce line breaks:<screen>nano -w</screen>
			</para>
			<para>For more information about how to use <application>nano</application>, refer to the <ulink url="&wiki-Nano;">guide on the wiki</ulink>.
			</para>
			<para>There are also quite a few other terminal-based editors available in Ubuntu, popular ones include <application>VIM</application> and <application>Emacs</application> (the pros and cons of each are cause for much friendly debate within the Linux community). These are often more complex to use than <application>nano</application>, but are also more powerful.
			</para>
	</sect1>


</chapter>
