<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % cdo-C SYSTEM "../../../libs/cdo-C.ent">
%cdo-C;
]>
<article>
	<articleinfo>
<title>Contribute To Ubuntu</title>

	<legalnotice>
	<title>Credits and License</title>
	<para>The Ubuntu Documentation Team maintains this document.</para>
	&licenses;
	</legalnotice>
	&copyright;
	<authorgroup>
		&author-ubuntu-documentation-project;
	</authorgroup>
	&disclaimer;
	&publisher;
  </articleinfo>

	<para>
<emphasis role="strong">Introduction</emphasis>
</para>
	<para>
Ubuntu is most of all a community. All of the software, artwork and documentation in Ubuntu has been created, tested, used and discussed openly by people around the world participating in the Open Source community made possible by the Internet. Anyone who uses Ubuntu is part of this global community, and we invite you to help shape Ubuntu to better meet your needs. To make it yours! 
</para>
	<para>
Anyone can help shape and improve Ubuntu. This document will introduce you to the most common ways that you can contribute to Ubuntu: by using Ubuntu in your everyday life and recommending it to others, by helping other users, by translating programs or documents to your native language, by testing the software and reporting issues, by creating artwork or writing documentation, by fixing software issues, writing new software or keeping others' software up to date. 
</para>
	<para>
Many of these tasks do not require special technical skills - in the Ubuntu community, you don't have to be a programmer to get involved! Have a look at this document and see what catches your interest. If you find mention of collaborative tools or means of online communication that you are unfamiliar with, you can read more about these in the <emphasis>Participating in the Ubuntu Community</emphasis> section. 
</para>
	<para>
No matter how you want to contribute, we will welcome new drive and ideas and any contributions to improve Ubuntu and spread Open Source to the world.  
</para>
<para/>
  <section>
    <title>Spreading the Word</title>
    <para>The easiest way to give back to the Ubuntu community is
    by sharing Ubuntu with others: Recommend Ubuntu to others, show
    them how to download and install Ubuntu and the possibilities
    and qualities of Open Source Software. As the Ubuntu community
    grows, so does its influence and the more accepted and
    supported Ubuntu will become! You can spread the word
    by:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Ordering CDs from Shipit and give them to people who
        might be interested. Drop them off at libraries, Internet
        Cafes, schools, computer shops or anywhere else where
        people use computers. Be sure to help people to use and
        understand Ubuntu if they become interested.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Give a talk at your local school, Linux User Group or
        library on Ubuntu! There are lots of notes from other
        Ubuntu talks given by others in several languages are
        available on the wiki.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Write a short account of how and why you use Ubuntu
        by following these guidelines and send it to 
        <ulink url='mailto:mystory@ubuntu.com'>
        mystory@ubuntu.com</ulink>. Your story can then be used to
        show others how Ubuntu can be used!</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Join or start a Local Community Team - if you like
        Ubuntu, it is likely that others around you like it as
        well! See <xref linkend="loco"/> for details.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <section>
      <title>Marketing</title>
      <para>If you want to help promoting and marketing Ubuntu in a
      more general and coordinated effort, you can join the Ubuntu
      Marketing Team which coordinates a number projects including
      the Fridge, the community-driven news hub for all things
      Ubuntu, and the Ubuntu Weekly News - a weekly update on
      Ubuntu development.</para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Read the 
          <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/MarketingTeam'>
          MarketingTeam</ulink> wiki page.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Join the 
          <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-marketing'>
          ubuntu-marketing mailing list</ulink></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Join the #ubuntu-marketing IRC channel on
          &irc-server;</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Ubuntu Women</title>
      <para>If you are a woman wanting to get involved in the
      Ubuntu community, or if you're a man interested in increasing
      the diversity of the Ubuntu community, you can join the
      Ubuntu-Women team which focuses on:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Encouraging women to use Ubuntu and especially to
          participate in the Ubuntu community.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Mentoring women in specific areas (such as
          technical, documentation, translation and communication)
          so they have the information and support to get
          involved.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Openly discussing issues facing women and their
          involvement in Ubuntu (and Linux) and how to address
          them.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Read the 
          <ulink url='http://www.ubuntu-women.org/'>Ubuntu Women
          website</ulink></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Join the 
          <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-women'>
          ubuntu-women</ulink> mailing list.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Join the #ubuntu-women IRC channel on
          &irc-server;</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="loco">
    <title>Going Local!</title>
    <para>Chances are that you are not the only person in your
    city, region or country who is using Ubuntu. You can help to
    make Ubuntu better for people in your area by helping out local
    Ubuntu users or translating the Ubuntu software and
    documentation to your local language.</para>
    <section>
      <title>LoCo teams</title>
      <para>if you want to meet other Ubuntu users in your area,
      you should look for a Local Ubuntu Community team (Lo
      <emphasis role='strong' />Co team for short) to join. There
      are Lo
      <emphasis role='strong' />Co teams spread out all over the
      world, and you can find a list of all of them 
      <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/LoCoTeamList'>
      here</ulink>. If there isn't a Lo
      <emphasis role='strong' />Co team near you, you can start a
      new one! Just follow the 
      <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/LoCoTeamHowto'>
      instructions</ulink> on the wiki.</para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Read the 
          <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/LoCoTeams'>
          LoCoTeams</ulink> wiki page.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Join your local Lo
          <emphasis role='strong' />Co Team mailing list and IRC
          channel (details can be found on the 
          <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/LoCoTeamList'>
          LoCoTeam List</ulink> wiki page)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Translation</title>
      <para>If your home language is not English but you happen to
      have really good English skills and are comfortable using
      software in English, you help to translate the Ubuntu
      applications and documentation into your native language. To
      help out you can:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use the web-based 
          <ulink url='https://launchpad.net/distros/ubuntu/+translations'>
          Rosetta translation system</ulink> makes it easy to
          translate Ubuntu applications into your language. Even if
          you just translate a few lines you may make all the
          difference to someone in your own country who is just
          starting to learn about computers and Free
          Software.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Translate popular wiki pages within the
          Documentation Wiki.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Test that your local language fonts and display
          works correctly. If they don't, file bug reports on the
          issues.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Join your local Lo
          <emphasis role='strong' />Co Team mailing list and IRC
          channel (details can be found on the 
          <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/LoCoTeamList'>
          LoCoTeam List</ulink> wiki page) to get in touch with
          other users in your region so you can coordinate your
          translation efforts.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Join the 
          <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-translators'>
          Ubuntu-Translators mailing list</ulink> to stay in touch
          with other Ubuntu translators.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Helping others with Ubuntu</title>
    <para>You can make a major contribution to the Ubuntu project
    by helping others use Ubuntu. There are four main community
    support channels where you can help out other Ubuntu users by
    answering questions and referring them to relevant
    documentation:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Join the 
        <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-users'>
        Ubuntu support mailing list</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Join the Ubuntu support and discussion IRC channel:
        #ubuntu on &irc-server;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Join the 
        <ulink url='http://www.ubuntuforums.org/'>Ubuntu
        Forums</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Check the 
        <ulink url='https://launchpad.net/distros/ubuntu/+tickets'>
        Launchpad Support Tracker</ulink> for support requests for
        Ubuntu that you can help out with.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
    <emphasis role='strong'>NB:</emphasis> If you prefer to help
    other Ubuntu users in another language than English, please
    refer to the 
    <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/LoCoTeamList'>LoCoTeam
    list</ulink> for info on local language support options where
    you can help out.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Helping others with Kubuntu, Edubuntu or
      Xubuntu</title>
      <para>If you want to help users specifically with issues
      concerning a derivative version of Ubuntu, each of these have
      their own support IRC channels on &irc-network;, as well as their
      own mailing lists. The Ubuntu derivatives are also supported
      on the 
      <ulink url='http://www.ubuntuforums.org/'>Ubuntu
      Forums</ulink>.</para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>Kubuntu</emphasis>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Join the 
          <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/kubuntu-users'>
          Kubuntu support mailing list</ulink>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Join the Kubuntu support and discussion IRC
          channel: #kubuntu on &irc-server;</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>Edubuntu</emphasis>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Join the 
          <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/edubuntu-users'>
          Edubuntu support mailing list</ulink>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Join the Edbuntu support and discussion IRC
          channel: #edubuntu on &irc-server;</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>Xubuntu</emphasis>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Join the Ubuntu support and discussion IRC channel:
          #xubuntu on &irc-server;</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>New User Network</title>
      <para>If you want to help others who are learning how to use
      Ubuntu, you can join the New User Network - a group of
      community supporters who spend 10 or so hours a week helping
      new users.</para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Read the 
          <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/NewUserNetwork'>
          NewUserNetwork</ulink> wiki page</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Join the #ubuntu-nun IRC channel on
          &irc-server;</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Usability</title>
      <para>If you want to improve the 
      <emphasis>usability</emphasis> of Ubuntu, you can try out one
      of the Ubuntu usability tests on your friends, and record
      their reactions and impressions of Ubuntu. You can then
      report these impressions to the Ubuntu Desktop team.</para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Read the 
          <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/UsabilityTesting'>
          UsabilityTesting</ulink> wiki page</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Join the 
          <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-desktop'>
          ubuntu-desktop mailing list</ulink></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Accessibility</title>
      <para>If you are interested in making Ubuntu and its
      derivatives usable by as many people as possible across ages,
      language and physical abilities, you can help the Ubuntu
      Accessibility Team with improving the accessibility support
      on the Ubuntu platform and the software that runs on
      it.</para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Read the 
          <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/Accessibility/Team'>
          Accessibility Team</ulink> wiki page</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Join the 
          <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-accessibility'>
          ubuntu-accessibility mailing list</ulink></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Join the #ubuntu-accessibility IRC channel on
          &irc-server;</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Participate on the 
          <ulink url='http://www.ubuntuforums.org/forumdisplay.php?f=145'>
          Accessibility section of the Ubuntu Forums</ulink></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Writing Documentation</title>
    <para>If you get stumped by a problem with Ubuntu, chances are
    good that many other people will be frustrated by it as well.
    If you are not currently able to write code to fix the problem,
    you can help everyone else out by writing up your experience
    and documenting the solution! All documentation and help pages
    in Ubuntu are written by volunteer community members gathered
    in the Ubuntu Documentation Team, and you can help out in a
    number of ways:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Check the existing documentation to see if it covers
        your problem. If it does, you can add to it, edit it or
        remove errors (such as typos, grammar and spelling, and
        technical errors), send any suggestions and changes to the
        Documentation Team mailing list.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If no relevant documentation exists, you can add a
        page in the Documentation Wiki which is a separate
        community wiki for editing and writing documentation.
        Rather than answer a question two or more times, write up
        the answer and make it available to everyone in the
        wiki.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Read through the HOWTOs and other documentation in
        the Ubuntu Forums and check them for accuracy, and put them
        in the Documentation Wiki.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Join one of the Documentation Team projects and work
        on directly on maintaining and developing one of the guides
        for Ubuntu or one of its derivatives. A new version of
        these guides are released with each new release of Ubuntu,
        and these are translated through the translation tool
        Rosetta in the same manner as all other applications in
        Ubuntu.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Read the 
        <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/DocumentationTeam'>
        Documentation Team</ulink> wiki page</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Join the 
        <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-doc'>
        Documentation team mailing list</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Join the #ubuntu-doc IRC channel on
        &irc-server;.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <section>
      <title>Wiki</title>
      <para>You can spell check, edit or write the pages of the
      Ubuntu wiki. The better and more accessible the information
      in the wiki is, the easier it will be for people to use. You
      can find a list of pages in need of editing on the 
      <ulink url='https://help.ubuntu.com/community/WikiToDo'>Wiki
      To Do</ulink> page. The Wiki is maintained by the Wiki Team -
      a group of active wiki contributors that edit and clean up
      the main Ubuntu wiki according to community-maintained 
      <ulink url='https://help.ubuntu.com/community/WikiGuide'>Wiki
      Guidelines</ulink>.</para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Read the 
          <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/WikiTeam'>Wiki
          Team</ulink> wiki page</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Join the 
          <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-doc'>
          Documentation team mailing list</ulink> and the
          #ubuntu-doc IRC channel on &irc-server; - both of
          which are also used for Wiki Team discussion.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Creating Artwork</title>
    <para>If you have artistic talent, you can help improve the
    style and feel of the Ubuntu desktop by contributing to the
    artwork and design of the next release of Ubuntu. All of the
    splash screens, icons, wallpapers and sounds of Ubuntu are
    designed, discussed and approved by the Ubuntu Artwork team,
    and you can help out by examining the current approved Ubuntu
    artwork projects at 
    <ulink url='https://launchpad.net/people/ubuntu-art/+specs' /> and
    create something that will fit with what is being planned with
    the next release of Ubuntu.</para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Read the 
        <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/Artwork'>Art
        Team</ulink> wiki page</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Join the 
        <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/Ubuntu-art'>
        Ubuntu-art mailing list</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Join the #ubuntu-artwork IRC channel on
        &irc-server;.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Testing and Bug squashing</title>
    <para>Ubuntu, like any other software, needs good testers. You
    can contribute to Ubuntu simply by running the latest version
    and reporting software issues - we call them bugs - and helping
    to manage those bugs until they are fixed.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Software Testing</title>
      <para>All software-specific bugs is the domain of the Ubuntu
      Bugsquad which is the Quality Assurance (QA) team for Ubuntu.
      Getting involved with the Bugsquad is easy:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Join the Ubuntu devel-announce mailing list to get
          all of the announcements of when a new development
          version of Ubuntu is released. The development version of
          Ubuntu is the one that the developers are currently
          working on, so they're usually quite unstable and full of
          bugs.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Download and install the latest development version
          of Ubuntu, and upgrade it regularly. You can download the
          Ubuntu development version here. Do not use a development
          release as your main operating system, if you feel
          comfortable using an operating system that may break with
          a new upgrade.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>You will run into problems when you run a
          development version of Ubuntu, when you do you should
          report those problems as bugs in the Ubuntu bug tracker.
          Unless you let the developers know of the bugs you
          encounter, they won't be able to fix them as they need
          information on under which circumstances these bugs
          occur.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>When you find a bug, you should report bugs into
          the Ubuntu Bug tracker. You should check that the bug
          hasn't already been reported by searching for it. If you
          find the bug already reported, you can add a comment of
          your own about it, or change its status to "Confirmed".
          If the bug hasn't been reported, you can file a new bug
          report. Read the 
          <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/HelpingWithBugs'>
          HelpingWithBugs</ulink> wiki page to learn more about what
          information the developers will need to fix the
          bug.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>You can make a huge impact by fixing bugs yourself,
          and thus improve Ubuntu!</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Read the 
          <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/BugSquad'>
          BuqSquad</ulink> wiki page</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Join the #ubuntu-bugs IRC channel on
          &irc-server;</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Check the 
          <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/devel-announce'>
          devel-announce mailing list</ulink> for announcements of
          Bug days which are special occasions where the Bug Squad
          mount special efforts to teach new contributors how to
          find, reproduce, confirm and close bugs.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Hardware Testing</title>
      <para>All hardware-specific bugs - ie. bugs that only appear
      when certain hardware or certain combinations of hardware -
      belong to the the Ubuntu Testing Teams. With each new Ubuntu
      development release, it is necessary to test whether all of
      the Ubuntu system and associated applications still work with
      all kinds of hardware and peripherals. You can help by
      testing Ubuntu on your own hardware.</para>
      <section>
        <title>General Testing</title>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem override='none'>
            <para>The Ubuntu Testing Teams have made a list of
            things they need to test on every new development
            release. Run through the list and test each part as
            they apply to your setup. Note any failures and fill
            out a report and send it to the Ubuntu-devel mailing
            list.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Read the 
            <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/Testing'>
            Testing</ulink> wiki page</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the 
            <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/devel'>
            devel mailing list</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the #ubuntu-devel IRC channel on
            &irc-server;</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Laptop Testing</title>
        <para>If you have a laptop, you can join the Ubuntu Laptop
        Testing Team for laptop-specific testing.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Read the 
            <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/LaptopTesting' /> wiki
            page</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the 
            <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-laptop'>
            ubuntu-laptop mailing list</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the #ubuntu-laptop IRC channel on
            &irc-server;.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Server Testing</title>
        <para>If you run a server, you can join the Ubuntu Server
        Testing Team for server-specific testing.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Read the 
            <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/ServerTesting' /> wiki
            page</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the 
            <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-devel'>
            ubuntu-devel mailing list</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the #ubuntu-server IRC channel on
            &irc-server;.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>PDA Testing</title>
        <para>If you have a PDA you would like to use with Ubuntu,
        you can join the Ubuntu PDA Testing Team for specific
        testing to improve the Ubuntu PDA support.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Read the 
            <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/PDATesters'>PDA
            Testers</ulink> wiki page</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the 
            <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-devel'>
            ubuntu-devel mailing list</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the #ubuntu-devel IRC channel on
            &irc-server;.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>NB:</emphasis> Please note that none
        of these channels are support channels per-se, please use
        #ubuntu for that!</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Maintaining Ubuntu</title>
    <para>If you want to improve the software in Ubuntu, you can
    help by preparing - we call it packaging - Open Source software
    for use in Ubuntu and by fixing bugs in the software already
    included with Ubuntu.</para>
    <para>Ubuntu is constantly evolving and improving as the Open
    Source software it contains continues to be developed. Though
    many of these improvements are made by Ubuntu developers, most
    of the improvements are done by developers elsewhere in the
    Open Source world - these developers are what we call the 
    <emphasis>Upstream</emphasis> for Ubuntu as these improvements
    flow 
    <emphasis>downstream</emphasis> to Ubuntu.</para>
    <para>Most of the Ubuntu development work consists of taking
    these improvements and integrating them in Ubuntu while
    ensuring that they do not break any other part of the system.
    All software in Ubuntu is arranged in software packages called
    .deb files. Most of these packages are taken from the Debian
    distribution and merged and stabilized for use with Ubuntu,
    though others are prepared directly from the upstream source
    code.</para>
    <para>These software packages are sorted into two repositories:
    
    <emphasis role='strong'>Main</emphasis> which contains the core
    components of Ubuntu maintained by the core Ubuntu developers,
    and 
    <emphasis role='strong'>Universe</emphasis> which contains all
    the other software from the Open Source world. Unless you're
    already a proficient contributor to one of the core components
    in Ubuntu, you should begin with the Universe
    Repository.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Contributing to the Universe Repository (MOTU)</title>
      <para>If you know of a cool application, feature or change
      available else in the Open Source world that you would like
      to have in Ubuntu, you can add it yourself by packaging it
      for Ubuntu.</para>
      <para>All of the non-core packages in Ubuntu are in the
      Universe repository, and are maintained by the Ubuntu
      developers who humorously call themselves Masters of the
      Universe - or MOTUs for short.</para>
      <para>If you want to get involved with packaging, you can
      help out the MOTUs as a MOTU hopeful. The MOTUs are community
      members who have been granted upload rights to the Universe
      repository by the Technical Board, whereas MOTU Hopefuls are
      community members (like you) helping out, gathering
      experience and who one day may gain upload rights
      themselves.</para>
      <para>To get started as a MOTU hopeful you can:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Get in touch with a 
          <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/MOTU/Mentors'>MOTU
          Mentor</ulink> who will help you with the basics.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Read the 
          <ulink url='http://doc.ubuntu.com/ubuntu/packagingguide/C/index.html'>
          Packaging Guide</ulink></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Join the 
          <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/MOTU/School'>MOTU
          school lessons</ulink> that address relevant issues about
          package maintenance.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Look over the 
          <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/MOTU/Tasks'>MOTU
          Tasks list</ulink> to see which projects need help.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Once you have gained experience with packaging tasks
      (for example, by playing an active role in the MOTU team),
      you will be able to move from a universe-only maintainer to
      an Ubuntu core developer by .</para>
      <para>
      <emphasis role='strong'>NB:</emphasis> The MOTUs also maintain
      the packages for K|Ed|X|ubuntu and the other Ubuntu
      derivatives, so you if you want to contribute to one of these
      specifically, you will need to get involved with the
      MOTUs.</para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Read the 
          <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/MOTU'>
          MOTU</ulink> wiki page</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>join the 
          <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-motu'>
          ubuntu-motu</ulink>, 
          <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-devel'>
          ubuntu-devel</ulink> the ubuntu-devel and the 
          <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-devel-announce'>
          ubuntu-devel-announce</ulink> mailing lists.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Contributing to the Main Repository</title>
      <para>The core components of Ubuntu are maintained by number
      of specialized teams with their own area of responsibility.
      If you have a special interest in helping out in one of these
      areas, you can involved with that specific team.</para>
      <para>No matter what kind of contribution you would like to
      make to the core components of Ubuntu, we recommend that you
      join the 
      <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-devel'>
      ubuntu-devel</ulink> and 
      <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-devel-announce'>
      ubuntu-devel-announce</ulink> mailing lists. All information
      about technical development passes through those channels.
      You should also familiarize yourself with the details of the 
      <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/DeveloperResources'>
      Developer Resources</ulink> wiki page.</para>
      <section>
        <title>Desktop Team</title>
        <para>If you are especially interested in the Ubuntu GNOME
        Desktop, you can get involved with the Desktop Team which
        works to bring the latest cool GNOME desktop stuff to
        Ubuntu.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Read the 
            <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/DesktopTeam'>
            Desktop Team</ulink> wiki page.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the 
            <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-desktop'>
            ubuntu-desktop mailing list</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the #ubuntu-desktop IRC channel on
            &irc-server;</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Kubuntu Team</title>
        <para>If you are especially interested in the Kubuntu KDE
        Desktop, you can get involved with the Kubuntu Team which
        works to bring the latest cool KDE desktop stuff to
        Kubuntu.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Read the 
            <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/HelpingKubuntu'>
            Helping Kubuntu</ulink> wiki page.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the 
            <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/kubuntu-devel'>
            kubuntu-devel mailing list</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the #kubuntu-devel IRC channel on
            &irc-server;</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Edubuntu Team</title>
        <para>If you are especially interested in the Edubuntu
        Desktop, you can get involved with the Edubuntu Team which
        works to bring the latest educational software into
        classrooms all over the world.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Read the 
            <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/Edubuntu'>
            Edubuntu</ulink> wiki page.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the 
            <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/edubuntu-devel'>
            kubuntu-devel mailing list</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the #edubuntu IRC channel on
            &irc-server;</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Xubuntu Team</title>
        <para>If you are especially interested in the Xubuntu XCFE
        Desktop, you can get involved with the Xubuntu Team which
        works to bring the latest cool XCFE desktop stuff to
        Xubuntu.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Read the 
            <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/Xubuntu'>
            Xubuntu</ulink> wiki page.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the 
            <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/xubuntu-devel'>
            kubuntu-devel mailing list</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the #xubuntu IRC channel on
            &irc-server;</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Server Team</title>
        <para>If you are especially interested in the Ubuntu
        Server, you can get involved with the Server Team which
        works to bring the latest system administration tools and
        server applications to Ubuntu.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Read the 
            <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/ServerTeam'>Server
            Team</ulink> wiki page.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the 
            <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-server'>
            ubuntu-server mailing list</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the #ubuntu-server IRC channel on
            &irc-server;</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Laptop Team</title>
        <para>If you are especially interested improving the Ubuntu
        laptop experience, you can get involved with the Laptop
        Team which works to improve support for ever growing
        varieties of laptop hardware.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the 
            <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/laptop-devel'>
            laptop-devel mailing list</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the #ubuntu-laptop IRC channel on
            &irc-server;</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Kernel Team</title>
        <para>If you are interested in hacking on the Linux kernel
        specifically for Ubuntu, you can get involved with the
        Kernel Team.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Read the 
            <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/KernelTeam'>Kernel
            Team</ulink> wiki page.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the 
            <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/kernel-team'>
            kernel-team mailing list</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the #ubuntu-kernel IRC channel on
            &irc-server;</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>X Swat Team</title>
        <para>If you want to get involved with the Ubuntu version
        of X.org, a good place to start would be the X Swat Team
        which maintains X.org in Ubuntu.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Read the 
            <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/XSwat'>XSwat
            Team</ulink> wiki page.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the 
            <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-devel'>
            ubuntu-devel mailing list</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Join the #ubuntu-x IRC channel on
            &irc-server;</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Writing Code</title>
    <para>If you want to program brand-new features specifically
    for Ubuntu or redesign and develop current ones, there are
    several ways to get you started:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Look through the list of Ubuntu specifications on
        Launchpad. Pick one that interests you, and hopefully there
        should be enough information to begin with an
        implementation.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Look through the list of paid bounty projects that
        are registered for Ubuntu in Launchpad. Pick one that
        interests you and submit a proposal and references.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Write and package brand new software for Ubuntu.
        Contact the MOTUs to get new software into the Ubuntu
        Universe so that people can try it out and give you
        feedback. In time it may become part of the Ubuntu Main
        portfolio of applications that are available to all Ubuntu
        users by default.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      <emphasis role='strong'>Contact:</emphasis>
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Read the 
        <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/DeveloperResources'>
        Developer Resources</ulink> wiki page</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Join the 
        <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-devel'>
        ubuntu-devel mailing list</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Join the #ubuntu-devel IRC Channel on
        &irc-server;</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Giving Ideas and Feedback</title>
    <para>If you have ideas and suggestions on new features and
    improvements that you would like to see and help bring to
    Ubuntu, you can:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Add your ideas to the 
        <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/IdeaPool'>Idea
        Pool</ulink> for features you'd like to see in Ubuntu,
        products, marketing suggestions or any other ideas you'd
        like to add here. Before each new release cycle is
        initiated, the developers go through the Idea Pool and
        bring up any ideas that they like.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Write a specification - a short description what
        feature or improvement you would like to implement and why
        and how it should be implemented. All specifications for
        Ubuntu are tracked in Blueprint, the Specification tracking
        part of the Launchpad system. Writing a good specification
        is an art the finer points of which is discussed 
        <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/SpecSpec'>
        here</ulink>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Once you have written your specification, you will
        need to get it approved for inclusion in Ubuntu by the
        Ubuntu core developers. Specifications are approved at the
        Ubuntu Developers' Summit which take place at the beginning
        of each new development cycle. You will need to add your
        specification to the Summit listing in Launchpad and show
        up at the summmit and present your specification, lead
        discussion and submit it for approval. If you can't make it
        to the summit in person, you can either have another
        community member present it for you, or try to present
        through on-line chat or VOIP.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Another way to get your feature into Ubuntu is by
        packaging it for the Universe repositories and thus making
        it available to other Ubuntu users. This will make it
        possible for others to try it out before committing to
        having it as a standard feature of Ubuntu.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      <emphasis role='strong'>Remember that in the open source
      world, work counts more than talk so try to find friends or
      link up with people who can help turn your vision into
      reality.</emphasis>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Ubuntu Membership</title>
    <para>Anyone who has made significant contributions to the
    Ubuntu community can be recognized as an Ubuntu Member by
    applying for membership to the Community Council. Ubuntu
    Members play an essential role in Ubuntu governance as they may
    be called upon to vote on resolutions put to the members by the
    Community Council and generally confirm its decisions. You also
    need to become an Ubuntu Member in order to become an Ubuntu
    Developer or MOTU.</para>
    <para>As a Member you will get an email address @ubuntu.com and
    the right to carry Ubuntu business cards too (We'll supply the
    artwork, you print your own cards) Learn more about becoming an
    Ubuntu Member 
    <ulink url='http://www.ubuntu.com/community/processes/newmember'>
    here</ulink>.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Participating in an Open Source Community</title>
    <para>If you have little experience participating in or
    contributing to an Open Source community such as Ubuntu, it is
    easy to feel slightly intimidated by the many different
    channels of communication and specialized tools that the
    community members utilize to have discussions and share their
    work.</para>
    <para>Below we will give you a short introduction to all of
    these, as well as some pointers to which ones might be of
    interest to you at first.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Community Communication</title>
      <para>Like most online communities, Ubuntu exists through
      textual communication. You can find all the news,
      discussions, help, brainstorming and general silliness of the
      Ubuntu community in text in various forms.</para>
      <section>
        <title>General Communication</title>
        <para>There are a few central channels of communication
        that will make it easy for anyone interested to keep up
        with the happenings in the Ubuntu community.</para>
        <para>The 
        <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-announce'>
        ubuntu-announce mailing list</ulink>: All official release
        and community announcements are published on this
        low-traffic mailing list. All users of Ubuntu would do well
        to subscribe to keep up-to-date with general happenings in
        the community.</para>
        <para>The 
        <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-news'>
        ubuntu-news mailing list</ulink>: Every week, community
        members of the marketing team publish a new edition of the
        Ubuntu Weekly News (UWN). This contains the latest news on
        the Ubuntu community and is an easy way to keep up-to-date
        with the latest in the Ubuntu Community.</para>
        <para>The 
        <ulink url='http://fridge.ubuntu.com/'>Fridge</ulink> is the
        community news web site. It links to the latest news items,
        articles and community projects on Ubuntu. It also links to
        each issue of the Ubuntu Weekly News, and contains a
        calendar of upcoming Ubuntu events.</para>
        <para>
        <ulink url='http://planet.ubuntulinux.org/'>Planet
        Ubuntu</ulink>: In the open source world, a Planet is a
        collection of blog posts which is gathered and published
        together into a single combined feed, latest news first.
        Planet Ubuntu aggregates the blog posts of Ubuntu
        developers and contributors and provides a window into
        their work and lives. It is a fascinating way to learn more
        about how Ubuntu is developed.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>The Mailing Lists</title>
        <para>Almost all of the more formalized development and
        team coordination about the shape and direction of Ubuntu
        takes place on the Ubuntu mailing lists. All lists have
        archives so that you can easily read up on old discussions.
        These are available from the each list's individual
        information page which are linked below.</para>
        <para>You can read an 
        <ulink url='http://www.gnu.org/software/mailman/mailman-member/node5.html'>
        introduction to mailing lists</ulink> if you have little
        experience with such.</para>
        <para>When posting to the mailing lists, please observe the
        
        <ulink url='http://www.ubuntu.com/community/lists/etiquette'>
        mailing list etiquette</ulink>.</para>
        <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>NB:</emphasis> This is not an
        exhaustive list of Ubuntu mailing lists - see 
        <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/'>
        this list</ulink> for all the mailing lists of the Ubuntu
        community.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>Announcements and news</emphasis>
        </para>
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols='2'>
            <colspec colname='col_0' />
            <colspec colname='col_1' />
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>List</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Description</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-announce'>
                    ubuntu-announce</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>All official release and community
                  announcements are posted on this low-traffic
                  mailing list.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-devel-announce'>
                    ubuntu-devel-announce</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>All developer-related announcements and
                  information - including announcements of new
                  development releases and development team
                  meetings</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-security-announce'>
                    ubuntu-security-announce</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Announcements of security updates to Ubuntu
                  releases. If you are an administrator for
                  multiple machines it is strongly recommended that
                  you subscribe to this list to be notified of
                  critical updates that may affect your system
                  security.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-news'>
                    ubuntu-news</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Weekly news bulletins on the Ubuntu
                  community for both users and developers</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>Support</emphasis>
        </para>
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols='2'>
            <colspec colname='col_0' />
            <colspec colname='col_1' />
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/edubuntu-users'>
                    ubuntu-users</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Ubuntu Help and User Discussions - 
                  <emphasis role='strong'>high
                  traffic!</emphasis></para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/edubuntu-users'>
                    kubuntu-users</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Kubuntu Help and User Discussions</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/edubuntu-users'>
                    edubuntu-users</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Edubuntu Users Help and Discussion</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>Ubuntu Development</emphasis>
        </para>
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols='2'>
            <colspec colname='col_0' />
            <colspec colname='col_1' />
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-devel'>
                    ubuntu-devel</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Ubuntu Developer Discussion mailing list is
                  for highly-technical discussions and
                  implementation details regarding current
                  development on Ubuntu.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/kernel-team'>
                    kernel-team</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Kernel team discussions</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/laptop-devel'>
                    laptop-devel</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>laptop-specific development</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-desktop'>
                    ubuntu-desktop</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>GNOME Desktop Team co-ordination and
                  discussion</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/kubuntu-devel'>
                    kubuntu-devel</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Kubuntu Developer Discussion</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/edubuntu-devel'>
                    edubuntu-devel</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Edubuntu development discussion</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/xubuntu-devel'>
                    xubuntu-devel</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Xubuntu Development Discussion</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/Ubuntu-motu'>
                    Ubuntu-motu</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>mailing list for the Masters Of The
                  Universe package maintainers</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>-changes</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>archive upload notification list - one for
                  each release, sorted by codename. Find them all 
                  <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/'>
                  here</ulink>.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/Ubuntu-DCT'>
                    Ubuntu-DCT</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Mailing list for the Debian Collaboration
                  Team</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>Ubuntu Testing and Quality
          Assurance</emphasis>
        </para>
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols='2'>
            <colspec colname='col_0' />
            <colspec colname='col_1' />
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/Ubuntu-bugsquad'>
                    Ubuntu-bugsquad</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Ubuntu Bugsquad mailing list. Currently
                  most bug discussion takes place in the
                  #ubuntu-bugs IRC channel</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/laptop-testing-team'>
                    laptop-testing-team</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Ubuntu laptop testing discussion and
                  announcements</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>Other Ubuntu teams</emphasis>
        </para>
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols='2'>
            <colspec colname='col_0' />
            <colspec colname='col_1' />
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-marketing'>
                    ubuntu-marketing</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Discussion on the community-based marketing
                  of Ubuntu</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-doc'>
                    ubuntu-doc</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Documentation team coordination and
                  discussion</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-art'>
                    ubuntu-art</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Discussion on Ubuntu artwork</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/Ubuntu-accessibility'>
                    ubuntu-accessibility</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Discussion and development of Ubuntu
                  accessibility</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-translators'>
                    ubuntu-translators</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Discussion about translating Ubuntu</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-women'>
                    ubuntu-women</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Discussion for the Ubuntu Women team,
                  including initiatives to improve the diversity of
                  the Ubuntu community</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>A list of all the Local Community teams can
                  be found 
                  <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/LoCoTeamList'>
                  here</ulink></para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>Community lists</emphasis>
        </para>
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols='2'>
            <colspec colname='col_0' />
            <colspec colname='col_1' />
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>
                    <ulink url='https://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/sounder'>
                    sounder</ulink>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Ubuntu community discussion, usually
                  on-topic when off-topic on the other mailing
                  lists. Sounder is the correct term for a pack of
                  warthogs - a reference to an early nickname for
                  the Ubuntu developers.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>IRC channels</title>
        <para>The more informal day-to-day chat, discussion and
        short-term coordination takes place on the community IRC
        channels on &irc-server;. Most of the main channels are
        
        <ulink url='http://people.ubuntu.com/~fabbione/irclogs/'>
        logged</ulink>, so that it is easy to look up a previous
        discussion for reference.</para>
        <para>If you are completely new to IRC, you can 
        <ulink url='http://www.irchelp.org/irchelp/new2irc.html'>
        learn more about IRC</ulink>, and learn 
        <ulink url='https://help.ubuntu.com/community/XChatHowto'>
        how to set it up in Ubuntu</ulink>.</para>
        <para>Please be sure to follow the 
        <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/IrcGuidelines'>IRC
        guidelines</ulink> when participating on the Ubuntu IRC
        channels.</para>
        <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>NB:</emphasis> This is not an
        exhaustive list of Ubuntu IRC channels - see 
        <ulink url='https://help.ubuntu.com/community/InternetRelayChat'>
        this wiki page</ulink> for all the IRC channels of the
        Ubuntu community.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>Meeting channel:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols='2'>
            <colspec colname='col_0' />
            <colspec colname='col_1' />
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#ubuntu-meeting</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>All team and council meetings are held here
                  and scheduled on the 
                  <ulink url='http://fridge.ubuntu.com/event'>
                  Events calendar on the Fridge</ulink>.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>Support channels:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols='2'>
            <colspec colname='col_0' />
            <colspec colname='col_1' />
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#ubuntu</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Ubuntu help channel</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#ubuntu+1</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Help channel for development
                  versions</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#kubuntu</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Kubuntu help channel</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#edubuntu</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>main Edubuntu channel - including
                  support</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#xubuntu</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>main Xubuntu channel - including
                  support</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>School channels:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols='2'>
            <colspec colname='col_0' />
            <colspec colname='col_1' />
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#ubuntu-classroom</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Channel hosting bi-weekly tutorials for new
                  Ubuntu users</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#ubuntu-motu-school</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Ubuntu MOTU team schooling channel</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>Development channels:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols='2'>
            <colspec colname='col_0' />
            <colspec colname='col_1' />
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#ubuntu-devel</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Main Ubuntu development coordination and
                  discussion channel</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#ubuntu-desktop</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>The Ubuntu GNOME desktop team coordination
                  and discussion</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#kubuntu-devel</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Kubuntu development coordination and
                  discussion</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#ubuntu-kernel</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Ubuntu kernel team coordination and
                  discussion</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#ubuntu-motu</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Coordination of the Ubuntu MOTU package
                  maintainers' team</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>Ubuntu Testing and Quality
          Assurance</emphasis>
        </para>
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols='2'>
            <colspec colname='col_0' />
            <colspec colname='col_1' />
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#ubuntu-bugs</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Channel for Bugdays</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#ubuntu-laptop</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Ubuntu laptop testing and
                  development</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#ubuntu-server</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Ubuntu server testing and
                  development</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
        <para>
          <emphasis role='strong'>Other Team channels:</emphasis>
        </para>
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols='2'>
            <colspec colname='col_0' />
            <colspec colname='col_1' />
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#ubuntu-doc</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Ubuntu documentation team discussion and
                  coordination</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#ubuntu-marketing</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Ubuntu Marketing Team discussion and
                  coordination</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#ubuntu-fridge</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>The Ubuntu Fridge community news site
                  discussion and coordination</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#ubuntu-women</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Discussion channel for the Ubuntu women
                  team</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#ubuntu-accessibility</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Coordination for the Accessibility
                  Team</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#ubuntu-locoteams</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Coordination of all local community
                  teams</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#ubuntu-translators</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Coordination and discussions about Ubuntu
                  translations</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>#edubuntu-doc</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
                  <para>Edubuntu documentation team
                  discussion</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Web Forums</title>
        <para>The 
        <ulink url='http://ubuntuforums.org/index.php'>Ubuntu Web
        Forums</ulink> were initiated independently by Ubuntu
        enthusiasts within a week of the first Ubuntu release.
        Since then, the forums have become a central part of the
        Ubuntu community. The web forums provide an excellent place
        for to get support and discuss the future of Ubuntu without
        subscribing to high-traffic mailing lists and cluttering
        your inbox. Unfortunately, very few of the core Ubuntu
        developers read the forums regularly, so if you want to get
        in touch with them, your best bet would be to contact them
        on IRC or on the mailing lists, rather than in the
        forums.</para>
        <para>When posting on the Ubuntu Web Forums, please observe
        
        <ulink url='http://ubuntuforums.org/index.php?page=policy'>
        the forum guidelines</ulink>.</para>
        <para>A complete list of the Ubuntu Web Forums and
        subforums can be found on the 
        <ulink url='http://ubuntuforums.org/index.php'>Web Forums
        front page</ulink>. There is also a list of Web Forums 
        <ulink url='http://www.ubuntu.com/community/forums'>for
        speakers of other languages than English</ulink>.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Developers' Summits</title>
        <para>At the beginning of each new Ubuntu development
        cycle, the goals and features to be implemented in that
        cycle are discussed and shaped at the bi-annual Ubuntu
        Developers' Summits where all the core developers are
        present and all other community members are invited to
        participate. These summits typically take a full working
        week and most often take place at hotels with good
        conference rooms near international airports for easy
        access. It is at these summits that new feature ideas can
        be discussed and agreed upon. You can read 
        <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/DeveloperSummitProcess'>
        more about the Summit Process</ulink>.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Community Tools</title>
      <para>Along with the community communication channels and
      summits, there are some central web-based tools which are
      used by the Ubuntu community to organize the documentation,
      meeting agendas, bugs, translations and
      specifications.</para>
      <section>
        <title>The Ubuntu Wikis</title>
        <para>A 
        <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/HelpForBeginners'>
        wiki</ulink> is a series of webpages that anybody can edit
        and where changes can be revised and undone if necessary.
        You may have heard of the Wikipedia on-line encyclopedia
        which is also a wiki, albeit a very big one. Ubuntu has two
        separate wikis with different functions. Both of them are
        open for anyone to edit and improve, but you'll need to log
        in first so that other people can see who edited
        what.</para>
        <section>
          <title>The Documentation Wiki</title>
          <para>If you come across a solution to your support
          problem, you can help make it easier for others to find
          the same answer. The documentation that ships with Ubuntu
          is all written and maintained by the Ubuntu Community.
          You can contribute to the documentation in the 
          <ulink url='https://help.ubuntu.com/community/'>
          Documentation Wiki</ulink>.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>The Community Wiki</title>
          <para>The 
          <ulink url='https://wiki.ubuntu.com/'>Ubuntu Community
          Wiki</ulink> contains all other community documents apart
          from the Help Documents. Here you will find minutes from
          community meetings, detailed specifications, details on
          Ubuntu Summits and conferences, various policy documents
          and personal pages. You can explore the Wiki and learn a
          lot about the Ubuntu community in that way.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Launchpad</title>
        <para>
        <ulink url='https://launchpad.net/'>Launchpad</ulink> is a
        web platform containing a new system of online
        infrastructure for Open Source Software development. It is
        developed and maintained by Canonical Ltd., the company that
        also sponsors Ubuntu development. Launchpad seeks to
        integrate many of the online services needed for Open
        Source project development and to make it easy for
        different Open Source projects to collaborate and share bug
        reports,patches and translations. It is also meant to make
        it easy to coordinate Open Source volunteers in teams and
        projects. Many of the Ubuntu teams will ask you to 
        <ulink url='https://launchpad.net/+login'>register in
        Launchpad</ulink> in order to contribute to the team.</para>
        <section>
          <title>The Ubuntu Bug Tracker: Malone</title>
          <para>Whenever you come across something that doesn't
          work right in a computer program, it is most likely a 
          <emphasis>bug</emphasis> - a problem or error in the
          programming code. You can report bugs to make the
          developers aware of them so that they can fix them. You
          should be prepared to communicate with them, since they
          will often need additional information. Ubuntu uses a bug
          tracking system called 
          <ulink url='http://www.launchpad.net/distros/ubuntu/+bugs'>
          Malone</ulink> which is integrated with the Launchpad
          system. Be sure to check whether the bug you have
          encountered is already known before you file a new bug
          report. Every bug report helps to improve Ubuntu!</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>The Ubuntu Translation Tool: Rosetta</title>
          <para>All of the text in all of the applications in
          Ubuntu should be translated into any of the hundreds of
          active languages in the world. 
          <ulink url='https://launchpad.net/rosetta'>
          Rosetta</ulink> is an easy-to-use web interface integrated
          in the Launchpad system that allows translation of many
          software projects and documentation. You can begin
          translating Ubuntu to your native language right
          away!</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>The Ubuntu Specification Tracker:
          Blueprint</title>
          <para>
          <ulink url='https://launchpad.net/specs'>
          Blueprint</ulink> is the feature development tracker in
          Launchpad. It allows the Ubuntu developers to keep track
          of all the specifications that are to be implemented in
          the next version of Ubuntu. All community members can add
          write new specification that they would like to have
          implemented - though they should be prepared to discuss
          them with the developers and be willing to help out as
          needed.</para>
<section>
<title>The Ubuntu Revision Control System: Bazaar</title>
	<para>
All of the software packages in Ubuntu in maintained in a decentralized revision control system called 
<ulink url="https://launchpad.net/bazaar">Bazaar</ulink>
 which is another vital part of the Launchpad system. A Revision Control System allows the management of multiple revisions of the same software so that several people can collaborate and coordinate changes by incrementing each revision with a revision number associated with the developer who made the change. While most Revision Control Systems are centralized around one server containing the whole revision system, Bazaar is decentralized which offers a number of advantages over traditional systems. You can <ulink url="http://bazaar-vcs.org/WhyUseBzr">read more about the differences</ulink>. 
</para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  </section>
</article>
